<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first sermon of R. Sheldon priest, after his conuersion from the Romish Church preached before an honourable assembly at S. Martins in the Field, vpon Passion Sunday, &amp;c. Published by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852420</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1081:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first sermon of R. Sheldon priest, after his conuersion from the Romish Church preached before an honourable assembly at S. Martins in the Field, vpon Passion Sunday, &amp;c. Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Sheldon, Richard, d. 1642?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] B[eale] for Nathanael Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at S. Martins in the Fields.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17743:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17743:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST SERMON OF R. SHELDON PRIEST, after his Conuerſion from the <hi>Romiſh Church: Preached before an</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Aſſembly at S. <hi>Martins</hi> in the Field, vpon Paſſion Sunday, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 19. 7.</bibl>
               <p>The Law of the Lord is unſpotted, conuerting ſoules: the teſtimony of the Lord is faithfull, giuing wiſdome to little ones.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of a woman's head and two laurel branches, apparently not in McKerrow</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by I B. for NATHANAEL BVTTER. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17743:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17743:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPVL, and his much reſpected friend, Sir THOMAS GARDINER <hi>Knight, all happineſſe</hi> in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, I preſent this my Sermon vnto you, and place your worthy name in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thereof; thereby to ſhew my reſpectiue loue vnto you, &amp; to let you vnderſtand; that if there be any fault committed in the publiſhing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; that you ought to beare a great portion of the blame, who haue bin (amongſt very many others) earneſt. with mee to afford it publike attire. If the Pon ifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians be diſtaſted therewith, they may in ſome part thanke them ſelues; ſome of them haue beene too cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourous out of the relation either of ignorant, male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolent, or ſemi-popiſh hearers, in rumoring the ſame, to haue beene but a rouing diſcourſe, ſometimes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned; ſomewhiles vnlcarned; but alwaies very bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter againſt the Papiſts; ſo bitter, that in it, I branded all thoſe of that ſect and hereſic (excepting none what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer) with the vile marke of diſloyalty &amp; traiterous ſpirits. In conſideration whereof, I was eaſier induced to let it ſee light, and in ſo publike a habit to vndergoe all cenſures: and (to giue thereader ſome ſatiſfaction) this alſo the rather, becauſe through confuſe noiſes, and clatterings, of voices, and of dores (my ſelfe, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not leſſe then a whole houre in an open pew, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the deliuery of my Sermon;) the recollection of my memory was then ſomewhat confuſed: ſo that, for that cauſe, and through want of time alſo, I did not,
<pb facs="tcp:17743:3"/> nor could not pronounce all thereof, ſo fully, and in that ſort as I intended it. The ſcope thereof (kind Sir) being briefly and contractly (not intended for ſo publike, and ſo honourable an aſſembly) to delineat the ineſtimable perfections and dignities of Chriſt; to perſwade all my Auditours to a ſincere and moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous affiance for ſaluation in his onely blood: to moſt aſſured loyalties to their Prince, and Countrey, and to a deteſtation againſt all Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, Ignatian, bloody, and ſanguineous attempts, againſt the ſtate of this Church and Countrey: I doe not know any one of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ranke and calling, to whom a diſcourſe of this kind would prooue more acceptable, more welcome. Make acceptance of it (Sir) therefore, with that loue and reſpect, with which it is ſent; and doe mee this fauour, that if you heare any ſemi-papiſts, or anie that are leaning that way, or any other, doubtfullie to coniecture or ſurmiſe, whether my c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nuerſion bee from the heart or not; or for hope of preferment, to ſpeake as you haue heard, as you thinke, and perfectlie know of mee: for you know, and knew from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, from whom my encouragements haue beene; from God; from Ieſus Chriſt: whoſe name therefore, be euer magnified and bleſſed; to whoſe bleſsings, and gratious fauours, I commend both you and yours, for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my chamber, <date>this 28. of Aprill, 1612.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your worſhips moſt aſſured in Chriſt Ieſus, R. SHELDON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17743:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT S. MARTINS in the Field vpon Paſsion Sunday, &amp;c. 1612.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>HEBR. 9. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. 14.</bibl>
                  <p>For if the blood of Buls and of Goates, and the aſhes of a young Cowe being ſprinkled; purifieth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, as touching the purification of the fleſh: how much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who by the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit, offereth himſelfe without ſpot to God, purge the conſcience from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD moſt infinite, immenſe in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; in power incomprehenſible, and in the perfect poſſeſſion, of a conſummate happineſſe, conſiſting in an vnſpeakeable contemplation, comprehenſion, and fruition of his owne diuine Nature and eſſence: three perſons, and one God; from all eternities moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: at time appointed by his holy pleaſure, out of an admirable propenſion of goodneſſe, to communicate and diffuſe himſelfe, did produce and create (<hi>ad extra</hi>) without himſelfe this whole Vniuerſe, as an imperfect,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17743:4"/> yet very good ſhadow, and obſcure reſemblance of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo wiſely framed, that man, conſidering and admiring the beauties and perfections of the ſame, might ſurmount with his ſoule, &amp; eleuate his vnderſtanding aboue all, and by all that is in it, to contemplate (though obſcurely) that <hi>Holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Sabaoth; of whoſe Maieſtie, and Glory, Heauen &amp; Earth are ſo ful;</hi> and to vnderſtand, how infinitely more excellent, the maker of all theſe things is to be admired, and eſteemed. Whoſe infinitely wiſe goodneſſe alſo conſidering, how all the creatures, which he had produced, were but as very imperfect and defectiue ſhadowes of his moſt infinite excellency, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous more fully to diffuſe himſefe, reſolued in his eternall Conſiſtory, in an infinite, and a diuinely inexplicable ſorte, to imparte himſelfe to his creatures, by giuing and imparting his Sonne, conſubſtantial, and coaequall to himſelfe, to humane nature, to aſſume the ſame, into a Diuine vnitie, not of nature (for that is impoſſible) but of ſubſiſtence, of perſonalitie; in ſo admirable a ſort, that thereupon we may Chriſtianly beleeue and confeſſe, that God is become Man, and Man is become God, without all confuſion or permixtion of natures, in a moſt perfect, and ſweet vnitie of one perſon.</p>
            <p>This is that immenſe, that infinite communication of God to his creatures, ſo often fore prophecyed, ſo often promiſed by God; ſo longed for, ſo deſired, ſo expected both by God and Man, that as it may ſeeme, and, if I may ſo ſpeake, both God and Man, like women trauailing with childe, and longing for deliuerie trauailed with longing deſires for the accompliſhing of the ſame. Of the Sons longing deſires (intermitting now to ſpeake of the other two perſons of the moſt ſacred Trinitie) I dare boldy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme ſo much, becauſe he himſelfe long before his in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, hath ſo foreſpoken by the mouth of his holy Prophet and Wiſeman, <hi>Prouerb. 8. Deliciae meae eſſe cum filijs hominum, They are my dainties, my delicates</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17743:4"/> he) <hi>to be with the ſonnes of men.</hi> How is this otherwiſe, then as a man amongſt men? as the Son of man (a name in which our ſweet Sauiour being conuerſant vpon earth, much delighted, as my Catholike and religious Auditors well know) amongſt the children of men, amongſt the Sonnes of men. This infinite communication being made (then which a greater the omnipotent power and wiſedome of God, cannot thinke vpon or make) what was the purpoſe, and proiect of it? What was the obiect, and laſt end of the ſons longing deſires? I anſwere; but not without premitting the admiration and exclamation of the Prophet <hi>Eſay (Domine quis credidit auditui noſtro) O</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 53.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, who hath belieued our hearing, what we haue heard, or to whom is the arme of the Lord reuealed?</hi> I anſwere, that the proiect of this immenſe communication of God, this infinite eleuation of the manhood is, that this God himſelfe, ſhould be a ſacrifice, this man aſſumpted, ſhould die, this Man and God, this God and Man (O moſt diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely ſweet myſtery) ſhould be an expiation, and propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for the ſinnes of humane nature, that the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reuiued, and ſanctified in his blood, might be eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a moſt ſweet fellowſhip of diuine puritie and happineſſe; conſiſting in the contemplation, loue, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, fruition of this God, moſt bleſſed from, and for, all eternities.</p>
            <p>And as I deliuered before, how God to repreſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, did make this whole vniuerſe, as a booke for his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures, to looke vpon, and in it, to rende him, his glory, goodneſſe, and maieſtie: yet neuertheleſſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie profane, impious, and godleſſe men there haue beene, who would not know God, and who haue <hi>ſayd in their</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note> 
               <hi>moſt fooliſh hearts, There is no God.</hi> So likewiſe, before this admirable communication this moſt ſweet aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was to be made to be a ſacrifice, a propitiation for all man kinde, <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile:</hi> Good God! by how many legall ſacrifices and ſacraments? By how many rites and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17743:5"/> obſeruances? By how many expiations &amp; ſprinklings? of bloods, of waters, of bloods of Buls, Goates, Kiddes, Hee-goates, Lambes, yong Hefers, Turtle Doues, Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? was this admirable ſacrifice, and the infinite excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies thereof, preſignified, premonſtrated, and foretold? to giue vnto mankind, ſome certaine fore knowledge and beliefe of the immaculate <hi>Lambe ſlaine from the beginning</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of the world:</hi> to and for the ſaluation of all ſincere belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. And although, all that was appointed by God ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Law of nature, or vnder <hi>Moyſes,</hi> to foreſhew the infinite excellencie of this ſacrifice, were but as darke types, and imperfect ſhadowes, in reſpect of the trueth and body it ſelfe of this ſacrifice: yet, the incredulous Iewes, to whom the prophecies of Chriſt, and this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice were ſpecially made, might by the Sonne, haue come to perfect knowledge, and beleefe thereof: But the veyle of malice againſt the moſt meeke Lambe, our holy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; who taxed their vices, reproued their tranſgreſſions, condemned their Phariſaicall pride, blinded their eyes: eſpecially, the veile of pride, by which they gloried in the Law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> in the blood of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> of the workes of the Law; was it, which ſo cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuated their vnderſtanding, that they preſumptuouſly thought, they needed no ſuch a Meſſias, who by ſacrificing himſelfe, ſhould bee a propitiation, a reconcilement for their ſins: they rather, deſpiſed, diſeſteemed ſuch a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias, making him as a ſtumbling blocke, and ſcandall to their owne vtter ruine and perdition: by their ambitious thoughts, they proiected to themſelues, a Meſſias like ſome Soueraigne Lord, and mighty Monarch, who ſhould reſtore the temporall glorie of Iſrael, and extend his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions ouer the whole force of the earth: iuſt ſuch an other, as the ambitious Biſhop and Monarch of <hi>Rome</hi> challengeth himſelfe to bee, in his pretended Vicary for the Meſſias.</p>
            <p>Againſt this, their vnhappie incredulitie, the bleſſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17743:5"/> Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who once had beene a contumelious perſecutor of all religious worſhippers of this ſacrifice; doth moſt egregiouſly, and diuinely diſpute in his Epiſtle directed vnto them, out of the 9. Chapter, whereof the 13. and 14. verſes I haue choſen for my Theme; vpon which I purpoſe to diſcourſe. The which I ſelected, partly to proportion my diſcourſe to the ſeaſon, when we all are, or ſhould be, preparing and making a Quadrage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime, or fortieth, as a paraſceue of Chriſt his death and paſſion: partly, for my owne ſpeciall conſolation, who knowing not how to make any leaſt requital to my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for his vnſpeakeable Charitie, toward me, doe take (according to the counſel of the Prophet Dauid) <hi>the cup</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.</note> 
               <hi>of ſaluation into my hand and doe inuocate the Name of the Lord:</hi> for that he hath mercifully vouchſafed to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate me into the kingdome of his beloued Sonne Ieſus; making knowne to me, the myſterie of Chriſt crucified; and deliuering mee from the baſe ſeruitude of contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible creatures, weake elements, and the moſt idolatrous ſacrifice of the Maſſe, which humane inuentions hath moſt preſumptuouſly deuiſed, and ſet vp in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ſynagogue, as an abomination moſt deteſtable, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the one, and onely ſacrifice, and altar of the Croſſe: for which my happy deliuerance, his Maieſtie be bleſſed by me, and magnified for euer.</p>
            <p>When I firſt choſe this text to handle, I thought to ſpeake at large of euery branch thereof; but meditating thereupon, it became ſo fruitfull, that ſtore made mee penurious: and I could not but ſay in my ſoule, with learned <hi>Auguſtine, O mira profunditas eloquiorum tuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confeſſ. lib. 12 Cap. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Deus meus: mira profunditas, mira profunditas, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror eſt intendere in eam; horror honoris, tremor amoris. O wonderfull profoundeneſſe of thy ſpeeches my God! won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull profoundneſſe, wonderful profoundeneſſe: it is a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to thinke vpon it, a horrour of honour, a trembling of loue.</hi> Wherefore I reſolued to pretermit all allegorizing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17743:6"/> and moralizing vpon the figures, and eſpecially, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine my diſcourſe, to that blood, to that ſacrifice; in beleefe whereof, the ſaluation of vs all conſiſteth: wherein, as I doubt not, but that I ſhall be aſſiſted by your deuout and Chriſtian prayers; ſo I moſt humbly requeſt your kind acceptance of theſe firſt fruits and labours, from my ſelfe, a nouice-Preacher in the Church of England. I haue bin perhaps ouer prolixe (contrary to the faſhion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Orators) in my <hi>Exordium,</hi> before I come to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing of my Theme, and to the ſelecting of ſome ſpeciall braunch: wherevpon to inſiſt, a fault pardonable and excuſable with ſuch as are acquainted with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundneſſe of ſacred Scriptures, and Chriſtian myſteries: the deuout conſideration whereof, as it illuminateth the vnderſtanding, ſo it alſo repleteth the mind with ſuch a treaſurie of diſcourſe, that the religious chewer of ſuch a cudde, findeth greateſt difficultie to bee briefe, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, to diuide.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For if the blood of Bulles, and of Goates, and the aſhes of a young Cowe being ſprinckled, purifieth the vncleane, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the purification of the fleſh: how much more, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>This argument of the Apoſtle, which conſiſteth vpon a propoſition &amp; an inference, is of that kind, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Philoſophers (<hi>à minori ad maius</hi>) from a leſſe, to a greater; from a darke, obſcure, leſſer, and ſmaller truth, admitted by the Aduerſary, to inferre and euince a truth, cleerer, manifeſter, greater, and moſt certaine. If (ſaith the Apoſtle) the blood of ſuch contemptible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the weake, vncleane, and ſeruile ſprinckling of the aſhes of a young Cowe, mixed with water, can purifie the fleſh: <hi>how much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who by the eternall ſpirit, offered himſelfe vnſpotted to God, clenſe the conſcience from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God?</hi> Singular veſſel of election, how mightie is thy argument either to confound or conuert the incredulous Hebrews!</p>
               <p>Chriſtian and beloued Hearers, obſerue the <hi>Antitheſis</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17743:6"/> and oppoſitions of the Apoſtle, waigh his compariſons, betwixt blood and blood: one, baſe, filthie, corrupt, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile, contemptible: the other, honourable, moſt pure, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, free, excellent: the one, of Bulles, and Goates: the other of man, of a perfect, and moſt innocent, and holy man. As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, O ye Hebrewes, you haue bulles, goates, kiddes, lambes: wee haue Chriſt the Meſſias deſired, expected: you haue the ſprinckling of a few corruptible droppes, we haue incorruptible, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere droppes of Chriſt, diuinely vnited to his perſon: you haue the vncleane and durtie aſhes of a young cowe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixt with water; we haue the admirable ſprinckling of the diuine and humane nature, in vnitie of perſon: your ſprinckling is naturally vncleane, and corporally polluteth the takers: ours is moſt pure, ſanctified by the eternall ſpirit, beautified by the diuinitie it ſelfe: yours is a ſprinckling made vpon man, ours is a ſweet ſmelling ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice offered to God: your ſprinckling onely purifieth an outward kind of impuritie, and legall irregularitie; ours clenſeth and purifieth the ſoules and conſciences of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full offerers: yours, many, and often repeated, can neuer make the offerers perfect: ours, being one, and once on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered, hath found an eternall redemption, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally conſummateth all beleeuers: yours were not effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious for ſanctification: ours, ſo potent, that it giueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of grace, whereby we may be enabled to ſerue the liuing God. Chriſtian and religious hearers, is it not worthily written of this Apoſtle, <hi>Saulus autem, &amp;c. But</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul was comforted and ſtrengthened, and euery where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the Iewes, teſtifying that Ieſus is Chriſt.</hi> O incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Iewes! when I conſider the pride of your mindes, and withall, the baſeneſſe of ſuch creatures, and ſuch ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, vnder which you liued, in ſo toileſome a ſeruitude, I am aſtoniſhed to thinke, that you would reſt in ſuch weake ſacrifices, rites, ſacraments, ceremonies, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruancies, and would not ſeeke, nor receiue Chriſt, the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17743:7"/> Meſſias, and the true immaculate Lambe ſlaine from the beginning of the world, being offered vnto you.</p>
               <p>Thus much moſt briefly of the propoſition it ſelfe: for I haſten to the inference made by the Apoſtle: in which full of all Chriſtian conſolation, I obſerue and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, firſt, of whom the blood is, which is offered; to wit, of Chriſt; in theſe words: <hi>How much more, the blood of Chriſt?</hi> Secondly, I obſerue by whom, and through whom, this blood is offered, <hi>By, and through the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſpirit:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>by the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit.</hi> Thirdly, I diſtinguiſh, to whom it is offered; there; <hi>to God.</hi> Fourthly, I obſerue for what end, this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is offered; there; <hi>to cleanſe the conſcience from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God.</hi> Of theſe foure (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitting ſome other obſeruations which might be here made) in order.</p>
               <p>Touching the firſt, when I weigh with my ſelfe, whoſe blood it is, which is offered: I am wholly diſanimated from preſuming to decipher the excellencies, perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and eminences of his perſon. For, I beleeuing with faith, that he is both God and man; not onely man, nor onely God, but a Chriſt conſiſting both of God and man; a perfect ſuppoſit, a compleate Perſon; who though as Chriſt, had a beginning, and was not before the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; yet as touching his diuinity, and perſonality, hee was moſt perfectly, from all eternities very perfect God, of God, Sonne of the father; who in the fulneſſe of time, by a certaine inexplicable vnion became the Sonne of man, or rather the true and naturall Sonne of a woman, and the reputed Sonne onely of man, of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> his puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue father.</p>
               <p>Theſe things I ſay beleeuing with faith, the ſaying of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet (<hi>Generationem eius quis enarrabit</hi>)<note place="margin">Iſay 53.</note> 
                  <hi>who ſhall declare his generation?</hi> occurreth, and checketh my preſumption, that I bee not too bold a ſearcher of maieſty; leaſt I be oppreſſed, and confounded with the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17743:7"/> glory thereof. Yet, conſidering that the veile of <hi>Moſes</hi> is remoued, and the veile of <hi>Sancta Sanctorum</hi> is rent, at the dreadfull houre of Chriſts (<hi>conſummatum eſt) it is conſummated:</hi> and that the <hi>myſterie of Chriſt, the</hi> hope of our glory; <hi>which was hidden in ancient ages and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh in his Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians) <hi>is now made manifeſt to the Saints:</hi> I will, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording<note place="margin">Colloſ. 1.</note> to the rule of Chriſtian faith, with my beſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of wit, and learniug, (but alaſſe, what a nothing is all that, in reſpect of the excellency of the obiect, whereof I am to diſcourſe?) declare vnto you, what this Chriſt is, of whoſe blood we ſpeake: what this, (<hi>verbum abbreuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum) this abbreuiated word</hi> is, to ſpeake with the Apoſtle, in his Epiſtle to the Romanes is: if in this diſcourſe, I ſeem<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> briefe and obſcure, impute it to the eminency of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, which otherwiſe then defectiuely, cannot be ſpoken of, neither by the tongue of man, nor of Angell.</p>
               <p>With moſt ſubmiſſe reuerence therefore, we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicer Chriſt; firſt, with a reference to God and his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſecondly, with a reference, and relation to vs: Thirdly as he is in himſelfe. In the firſt conſideration, firſt of all, we conſider Chriſt, as the very terme, obiect, or bound, of the greateſt communication, or diffuſion, which the Almightie Trinity can make: ſo that, by the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the moſt bleſſed Trinitie, and peculiarly the ſecond Perſon, hath already made of his ſubſiſtence, and perſonality to the humane nature, the ſame bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (be it ſpoken vnder correction of faith, and with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe reuerence) is at a ſtop and ſtay, not potent to make a greater communication, then this which is already made, whereby Chriſt is made. For, iſ a ſubſtantiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of the diuinity it ſelfe, in the very diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were poſſible; (which yet cannot be granted, vnleſſe we wil ſubuert the very foundation of chriſtian religion) yet the ſame greater then this, which is alreadie made, ſhould, nor could not be: becauſe a greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17743:8"/> then of God himſelfe, which is already made, by this perſonall coniunction in Chriſt, cannot bee imagined. Againe, if either the father, or the holy Ghoſt, or both, (as Chriſtian diuinity faith it is poſſible) ſhould aſlume, by hypoſtatical and perſonall vnion the nature of an Angell or of man; yet both ſuch communications, both ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, ſhould not ſurpaſſe in greatneſſe, or excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, this one, which is already made in Chriſt alone. For our holie faith teaching vs, that two perſons of the moſt ineffable Trinity, are not greater then one, nor one of them leſſer then two; but that euery Perſon hath infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a perfect equality, and perſection with the other two: manifeſt it is, that the communications of two Perſons, or of three, is not greater nor excellenter then of one onely: How admirable therefore? how ineffable therefore is this communication of God to man, whereby the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent power of God is ſo bounded and limited, that it cannot proceed further, to make a worke of greater per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? O inenarrable generations! As the Eternall and natural generation of the ſonne <hi>in diuine eſſence,</hi> is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, ſo immenſe, that God the father could not beget a more perfect naturall Sonne: ſo like wiſe, the voluntary, and temporall generation of Chriſt, is ſo abſolute, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely perfect, that a greater cannot by God be made.</p>
               <p>Well, diddeſt thou crie out, holy <hi>Iſay (Generationem</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 53.</note> 
                  <hi>eius quis enarrabit?) who ſhall ſhew forth his generation?</hi> and againe, <hi>O Lord, who hath beleeued, what we haue heard, and the arme of the Lord to whom is it reuealed?</hi> Admirable indeed, but more ſweetly, and more comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably admirable is that, which the ſame Prophet adioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of this our Chriſt, that hee ſhould be reputed with the wicked, with malefactours; that through ſlander, and falſe iudgement, he ſhould be cut from the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, that he ſhould bee ſmitten by the ſenere decree of his father, for the expiation of the ſinnes of a moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and moſt vngratefull people. <hi>O Lord, who will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17743:8"/> what wee haue heard, or to whom is the arme of the Lord reuealed?</hi> not framing the heauens; but nailed and hanging vpon the Croſſe, to eleuate man with the might of his blood, to the heauens. But of this anone.</p>
               <p>This ſupreme communication of God to man, doth ſo farre ſurpaſſe all naturall productions of creatures, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall, of qualities of that kind; as of iuſtification, ſanctification, glorification, that there is no compariſon to be made: yea all the ſame graces, of iuſtification, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, glorification, by neceſſary conſequence, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vpon the ſame communication; and by vertue of the hypoſtaticall vnion; ſo, that it is impoſſible, that the ſoule or humane nature, which is aſſumpted into vnity of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Perſon; ſhould not by neceſſary conſequence, be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, be ſanctified, be glorified, beatified. And had not Chriſt, by his almighty power, bounded and limited the brightneſſe, which the ſoule and humane nature recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and poſſeſſed, by the viſion of the diuine nature, from redounding and imparting it ſelfe vnto his inferior parts, and his body: the ſame, by an effluence, and ouer flowing of happineſſe from his ſoule, ſhould haue become glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, glorified, and conſequently impaſſible, immortall; and ſo Chriſt could not haue died.</p>
               <p>But becauſe our deare Sauiour, (<hi>deſiderio deſiderauit) with a deſire deſired</hi> (as he teſtifieth of himſelfe) that is, moſt vehemently deſired, <hi>to drinke the cup of paſsion;</hi> and<note place="margin">Luc. 28.</note> to die the death, leſt the whole nation of mankind, for want of ſuch a death, ſhould haue periſhed. Therefore, (<hi>in capite libri</hi>) in the very head, beginning, or top of the booke, (as it is deſcribed in the 40. pſalme by ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings) in the very firſt moment of his conception, he gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly, and out of the bowels of an infinite mercy, vouchſafed by a great miracle to ſtop, and conteine the glory of his ſoule, from communicating, or redounding it ſelfe, to his body: that ſo, he might haue a fit, a ready, or<note place="margin">Pſal. 40. Heb. 10.</note> prepared body, as the holy Prophet and our Apoſtle doe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17743:9"/> ſpeake: a readie and prepared bodie, a bodie fitted to ſuffer. O ſweet Ieſus, had not thy bodie beene fitted for the perſon of thee a God, if it had not beene paſſible, apt to ſuffer, apt to die? No, no, ſaith our Chriſt, otherwiſe not fit: but being ſo fitted, ſo prepared, then ſaith Chriſt<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>(ecce venio) Behold I come, behold I come, to doe the will of my Father, and to die for the deliuerie of mankind.</hi> O Chriſtian and Catholike ſoules, are you not aſtoniſhed with admiration? Are you not incenſed and fired with flames of louing and moſt thankfull affections? to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that the very firſt miracle which Ieſus ſhould make, and this vpon the verie moment of his conception, was to containe the glorie, which by vertue of the Hypoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and perſonall vnion, would haue imparted it ſelfe to his bodie, and haue made it impaſſible and immortall, that by ſuch a miraculous ſubtraction and containing of glorie he might make his bodie paſſible, mortall, apt, and fitted to ſuffer, to die: for whom? for whom? for you Chriſtian hearers, and for all mankind. If vpon ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations you feele no alterations of loue, of ioy, of deteſtation of ſinne, of amendment of life, of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, of conſolation in your ſoules <hi>(Tentate voſmetipſos ne forte reprobi ſitis) Trie your ſelues</hi> to ſpeake with the<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.</note> Apoſtle, <hi>leaſt perhaps you be reprobate:</hi> trie and examine whether ſoules congealed, and obdurate in ſinne, not to be moued or melted by ſuch a fire of loue, are not reprobat,<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.</note> and neere to malediction.</p>
               <p>But, to our confiderations vpon Chriſt, whom if wee conſider, with reſpect to the diuine attributes, and infinit perfections in God, to wit, his infinite wiſedome, omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie, iuſtice, mercie, goodneſſe, &amp;c. they doe ſo perfectly ſhine and appeare in him, that moſt worthily therefore he is called in holy Scripture <hi>(facies Domini) the face of the Lord,</hi> (for ſo ſome thinke that is to be vnderſtood) in the<note place="margin">Num. 6.</note> booke of Numbers <hi>(oſtendat Dominus faciem ſuam) the Lord ſhew his face:</hi> and thoſe frequent ſpeeches in holy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17743:9"/> Scriptures, <hi>Shew thy face O Lord, Turne not away thy face, Illuminate thy countenance ouer vs.</hi> What other face or countenance of God is this, than that, of which Saint<note place="margin">Hebr. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> thus pronounceth? <hi>That he is the ſplendour of the glorie of his Father, and the figure of his ſubſtance.</hi> And I vnderſtand this ſhining and appearing of the diuine attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes in Chriſt, not onely in reſpect of his diuine eſſence, and nature, by which he is the ſonne of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to the common law of Sonnes, as a Sonne, he is like to his Father, nor in reſpect of any ſupernaturall gifts or qualities onely, or by reaſon of his ſoule; for theſe two later are common with him to iuſt and ſanctified per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: but moreouer, in a certaine admirable and inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſort, the diuine attributes did ſo ſhine, and were ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent in Chriſt, his humane nature and conuerſation, that by the ſame he might be knowne to be very God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as the ſex of man or woman is knowne and diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by their faces. May I not gather this out of that ſpeech of Chriſt to <hi>Philip? (Philippe qui videt me &amp;c.)</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Philip, he who ſeeth me, ſeeth my Father.</hi> Againe, <hi>if you had knowne me, you ſhould alſo haue knowne my Father.</hi> Cleare is this in S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the beloued Diſciple thus pronouncing.<note place="margin">1. Joh. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>(Quod fuit ab initio &amp;c.) That which hath beene from the beginning, which we haue heard, which we haue ſeene with our eyes of the word of life, that which we haue beheld, and our hands haue felt, of the word of life, and the life is made manifeſt, and we haue ſeene, and witneſſe, and doe ſhew to you the life eternall, which was with the Father, and hath appeared vnto vs.</hi> O admirable, diuine, and moſt beloued Diſciple in Chriſts conuerſation and apparition, thou diddeſt ſee with thy eyes, and feele with thy very hands God the life, the word, made fleſh. But tell vs, O ye Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Eaſt; yee, who being inuited and conducted by a ſtarre from heauen, came and found this our Chriſt in his mothers lappe, and hanging vpon her breaſts: what ſplendours of maieſtie? What beames of glorie did you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17743:10"/> behold in that Almightie infant? What, ſhall your gifts ſpeake for you? (<hi>Aurum, Thus, Mirrha</hi>) Gold, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Mirrhe, to a King, to a God, to a Man: who taught you this wiſdome? the Starre, or <hi>Balaams</hi> prophecie on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? no doubtleſſe: the diuine Maieſtie of that babe which you there beheld, in that garment of our humanitie, ſent forth ſuch ſplendours, to your great admiration, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the houſe, and finding the child with the bleſſed virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> as the Euangeliſt deſcribeth it, you could<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> not but proſtrate your ſelues, open, offer your gifts, your treaſures to him, Gold, Mirrhe, Frankincenſe; all which were myſticall gifts: for by Gold, the childs royall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and ſupremacie; by Mirrhe, his ſweet humanitie and mortalitie: by Frankincenſe, his Diuinitie and Godhead was ſignified, honoured, and adored. O conſummate wiſedome of theſe Sages from the Eaſt, honouring the maieſtie of this Almightie Babe, euen then, when the beames of his birth, reflecting vpon Hieruſalem, daunted and confounded <hi>Herod,</hi> with his Court, together with all the citizens of that earthly Hieruſalem. I will not ſtand to ampliare this my diſcourſe, by asking the Doctors and learned of Ieruſalem, what illuſtrations of wiſedome and knowledge they ſaw in this child, hearing the wiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres and demaunds which he made, being but twelue yeares of age: it is ynough for me, that the Scripture ſaith <hi>(Stupebant autem omnes &amp;c) But all who heard him, were aſtoniſhed, and amazed at his wiſedome and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> diuine wiſedome doubtleſſe appearing in him. Neither will I ſtand to demaund of the Apoſtles, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of this Chriſt, nor of the deuout multitude, what they ſaw, when to him, ſitting vpon a ſillie Aſſe, they gaue ſuch acclamations, excelling the condition of a pure man (<hi>Oſanna in excelſis &amp;c.</hi>) Health, Proſperitie, Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from on high: God ſpeed on high, Bleſſed is he who commeth in the name, in the power of the Lord: Bleſſed is he, who commeth the Lord, and with the power of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17743:10"/> Lord; the Lord, and God himſelfe. Six hundred paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſacred Scripture I paſſe ouer, recounting the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine wiſedome, mercie, power, iuſtice, goodneſſe of a God, ſhiningly appearing in Chriſt, and his conuerſation: ſo that euery where his diuine praiſes were breathed forth, either from the mouthes of infants, from the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his aduerſaries, or the religious applauſes of the deuout multitudes. But giue me leaue, moſt beloued and religious Chriſtians, yet to enter with this Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his paſſion, and there to conſider how magnificent and appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in it were the attributes &amp; perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head. I paſſe ouer his confounding, his caſting and throwing downe to the ground, his aduerſaries with traiterous <hi>Iudas</hi> comming to apprehend him, with thoſe few words onely <hi>(Quem quaeritis? ego ſum) Whom ſeeke you? I am, I am:</hi> whom you ſeeke, <hi>I am</hi> he: I pretermit hundreths of arguments in the time of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the proofe and honour of a ſuffering, of a dying Maieſtie. I onely conſider, what diuine ſplendours of goodneſſe, mercie, iuſtice, wiſedome, power, patience, clemencie, did with a collaterall reflection repreſent themſelues out of Chriſt crucified, and reflect vpon the right-handed, rather the right-hearted theefe, that hee was moued to make that moſt Chriſtian and happie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation<note place="margin">Luk. 23.</note> and confeſſion <hi>(Memento mei Domine, cum veneris, &amp;c.) Remember me O Lord, when thou ſhalt come into thy kingdome.</hi> O moſt happie confeſſion of a moſt happie theefe! fleſh and blood reuealed not this vnto thee. O thou theefe, not now a wicked theefe, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent theefe, robbing rather in a Paradiſe than vpon earth. O theefe, wonted with violence to violate men, but now, with the violence of a eontrite heart, liuely faith, and conſtant confeſſion, purchaſing Paradiſe. Chriſtian and religious hearers, what kingly, what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ornaments ſaw this moſt Chriſtian theefe, to make ſuch a confeſſion? to profeſſe Chriſt to be the King of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17743:11"/> heauen? for of any earthly kingdom he could not meane. The Scepter of the vaine reede, with the moſt ſcornefull, Haile king of the Iewes, he had not ſeene, he had not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps heard: the ſcepter he then beheld, were the ſharpe piercing nailes, faſtening his Kings hands, to the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full croſſe: the kingly robes, were <hi>Adams</hi> nakedneſſe, and our confuſion: the chaire of State, the hard and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious croſſe: the royall fare and kingly dainties, gall and vineger: the Prince-like acclamations, were tauntes, reproches, exprobrations, reuiles, with ſcornefull caſting of hands, and mouing of the heads of thoſe damned miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, with thoſe moſt contemptuous <hi>vahs: vah, vah, He hath ſaued others, let him now ſaue himſelfe: If he bee the ſonne of God, let him now come down from the croſſe, &amp; we will beleeue in him.</hi> I dare pronounce, that theſe moſt vnſpeakable ignominies, borne with that admirable pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, inuincible charitie, moſt charitable compaſſion and clemencie, and the powerfull ſuffering of Chriſt, did drawe this our holy theefe to that Chriſtian confeſſion; <hi>Remember mee, O Lord, when thou ſhalt come into thy kingdome.</hi> It was not the wonders onely, which mooued him thereunto: no, no; hee made this confeſſion before diuers of them were made, as you ſhall reade in Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> the 42. and 43. verſes of the 23. Chapter: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by the ſecret working of the holy Ghoſt, and by that confluence of the diuine attributes of patience, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, iuſtice, power, goodneſſe, charitie, which appeared in Chriſt (more then could be in a pure man) hanging vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, the good and Chriſtian theefe came to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him to be a Lord, and to confeſſe his eternall and euerlaſting kingdome.</p>
               <p>Oh, how could my tongue here expatiate it ſelfe, to amplifie by ſimilitudes and examples, how the attributes of a God euery where appeared in Chriſt! whether J be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him lying in the manger, or reſting in his mothers armes: whether amongſt the Doctors diſputing in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17743:11"/> Temple, or betwixt the theeues, praying, and offering ſupplications vpon the croſſe: whether ſcourging ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious buyers and ſellers out of the Temple, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, or himſelfe faſt bound to a pillar, tormented and ſcourged moſt cruelly by thoſe ſacrilegious executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners: whether ſitting wearie vpon <hi>Iacobs</hi> fountaine, or hanging languiſhing vpon the croſſe, yeelding forth of the blood of ſaluation a moſt pretious fountaine: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiſing the dead, or himſelfe adiudged to death: whether in the deſart feeding others with bread, or him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe fed by others with gall and vineger vpon the croſſe: whereſoeuer and howſoeuer, I ſee and contemplate him, J cannot but admire, and confeſſe him, (<hi>ſpecioſum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, prae filijs hominum) beautifull in forme aboue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men:</hi> beutiful in the forme of God aboue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men. I cannot but with admiration ſay vnto him with Kingly <hi>Dauid, Beautifull in forme aboue the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>of men, Grace is diffuſed in thy lippes: therefore thee, O God! thy God hath annointed with the oyle of gladneſſe, aboue thy fellowes:</hi> ſo annointed, that in verie forme he appeared more than his fellowes; aboue his fellowes not onely a holy man, but a God, God and man. I cannot but proclaime, that although the glorie of the Diuinitie of Chriſt, imparted to his ſoule, was ſo contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from communicating it ſelfe to his bodie, yet it could not be ſo concluded and ſhut vp, but that ſome beames and glitterings thereof did ſo diffuſe themſelues (like vnto the beames of the glittering Sunne vnder a cleare cloud) that the pious beholder might contemplate the very diuine attributes, to be in an admirable ſort relucent and reſplendent, in the very humanitie of Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing with man. O <hi>Emanuel!</hi> O <hi>Emanuel!</hi> God with vs: God with vs: conuerſing amongſt men, and by ſo diuine conuerſation, knowen to be the true <hi>Emanuel</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17743:12"/> the true God amonſt vs, amongſt men.</p>
               <p>Thus too breefly, and imperfectly, how theattri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and diuine perfections, of God were tranſponent in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Oh, that time would permit me, fully to conſider this our Chriſt, as he hath relation to the actions, and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God, in the framing, and gouerning of this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, eſpecially, his actions to ward mankinde! we ſhould find him, to be the very ſcope, and end, for which all this world was made; wee ſhould find him, to be the very drift, butte, and end of all Gods deſires; we ſhould finde, that of the holy Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> to be true in him (<hi>Et eris</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 62.</note> 
                  <hi>corona gloriae, in manu domini, &amp; diadema Regni in manu dei tui.) Thou ſhalt bee a crowne of glory in the hand of the Lord; a Diademe of a Kingdome in the hand of thy God.</hi> A crowne of glory, a Diademe of a Kingdome, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the head, and in the hands of the Lord, of God; to honour, to make glorious, God the Lord. A crowne of glory, A diademe of a Kingdome in the hands of God, in the hands of the Lord, euer to be looked vpon, to bee contemplated, admired, deſired. Heare the heauenly father, himſelfe more then once, auouching as much.<note place="margin">Math. 17. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. 1. Luc. 9. Mat. 3.</note> (<hi>Hic eſt filius meus, &amp;c. This is my beloued ſonne, in whom I am very well pleaſed,</hi> in whom my ſoule taketh full content. This, this, is the ſcope of all my actions; This is my word, which I looked vpon, framing the whole world. This is the very <hi>Idea,</hi> vpon which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templated, electing, predeſtinating, my children to my glory: and when I call thoſe, whom I haue elected, and predeſtinated, according to the purpoſe of my will, from all eternities; to iuſtifie them, to ſanctifie them, to glorifie them: I make them all confermable to the Image of this my ſonne: Yea ſo well pleaſed is my ſoule in him that for his ſake, from all eternities, I haue abſolutely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17743:12"/> perfectly, loued thoſe, whom I haue elected in him, and for him, before they were any thing at all, and when in time, like fugitiue ſeruants, they were at enmity with me, through ſinne, liuing in ſinne, delighting in ſinne: I then, for his ſake, called, iuſtified, ſanctified them, leauing them not, vntill I bring them for reſpect of him to my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory, and vntill, I accompliſh my will in them, I will not ſurce aſe: no man ſhall take them out of my handes, no man ſhall ſtop the might of my election. This, this, Chriſtian hearers, as it is doctrine, full of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the faithfull, that haue a liuing and a ſanctifying faith, through and in this Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t: ſo is it not nouell but moſt ancient, Catholike, howſoeuer moſt commonly, the Pontifician Diuines teach and affirme, that the predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and election of Gods children; is not without preuiſion of their merits: and ſo making the merits of man, as a motiue of Gods eternall election; they ſhew themſelues, to be nothing leſſe, then Semipelagians; whole Pelagians, I would call them, if they taught theſe merits of man; without neceſſity of grace through, and in Chriſt. Merits we exclude (Chriſtian hearers) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are made as cauſes of predeſtination: but not good workes, as fruites of ſanctification, in which, God hath eternally preordained his elect to walke in.</p>
               <p>Sixe hundred places of ſcripture, (wherewith you learned in Gods booke, are acquainted) I could produce for the confirming of this truth: how that without works freely in Chriſt alone, we were loued, beloued, and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; before we were any thing at all; (except onely in Gods election,) yea and afterwards alſo, when in time, we became worſe then nothing, by committing ſinne (the which, as it is nothing of Gods worke, ſo for ſo much as it is mans worke, it maketh him worſe then nothing) yet for Chriſts ſake, man ſo wicked, ſo abhominable, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, iuſtified, ſanctified, according to the purpoſe of Gods eternall election.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17743:13"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17743:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17743:14"/> O ineſtimable! O vnſpeakable benefit therefore of Chriſt! O Chriſt! powerfull in the eternall prouidence of God, before creation, for our election: powerfull in time appointed, for our vocation, iuſtification, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: powerfull for our perſeuerance, and finall conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: ſo powerfull, and ſo precious in the ſight of God; that if God, (whoſe goodneſſe is ſo great, that he would ſuffer no ill; if he knew not how, to produce good thereout) had not foreknowne ſuch a remedy againſt ſinne; ſuch an anointed one; ſuch a Chriſt; for the curing of ſoules; he would neuer haue permitted <hi>Adam</hi> to haue ſinned, at leaſt wiſe, he would neuer haue permitted his ſinne, as a generall deluge, to haue ouer whelmed all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; ſo that as in a ſort, it may be ſaid: ſinne had not bin permitted, if ſuch a Sauiour, ſuch a Chriſt, could not haue beene ſent; haue beene prouided: ſo neither, ſuch a dying Sauiour; ſuch a paſſible Chriſt had not been ſent, if ſinne had not beene permitted. O myſterie of all myſteries! from the very profoundeſt of my ſoule, I proclaime; O Chriſt; moſt bleſſed, and eternally to be deſired; for if thou couldeſt not haue beene ſent, to expiate ſinne; the ſame had not beene permitted; and if ſinne had not been permitted, thou haddeſt not beeneſent, to ſeeke the loſt ſheepe of mankind: O infinite goodneſſe of God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I dare boldly pronounce, with ancient <hi>Gregory. (O Felix Adae peccatum, &amp;c.) O happy ſinne of Adam; which deſerued to haue ſuch, and ſo great a Redeemer? O truely neceſſary ſinne of Adam; which by the death of Chriſt, is aboliſhed</hi> and deſtroied; of Chriſt I ſay, of whoſe excellencies and perfections, in reſpect of vs; and in the manner of his concurrence to our ſanctification, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, in reſpect of euery ſort of cauſing and working as materiall, formall, efficient, finall; and in reſpect of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for thoſe treaſures of diuine wiſdome, and graces, without meaſure, (as farre as the right hand of God, by his ordinary power could extend it ſelfe) imparted to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17743:14"/> his ſoule: if I ſhould further, (according to my diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made aboue of the reſpects of Chriſt) diſcourſe<note place="margin">Hebr. 5.</note> and ampliate my ſpeech, it ſhould proue, to be <hi>(ſermo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpretabilis) a ſpeech vninterpretable,</hi> (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh) either by my ſelfe the ſpeaker, or by you the hearers, neither doth the time fauour me ſo much: He is God, what ſeek you? he is God: what deſire you? or why doe I yet preſume to ſearch?</p>
               <p>Conſider his attributes, his perfections, to day, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the more you ſhall ſeeke, the leſſe you ſhall find (if you thinke to attaine) for hee is incomprehenſible: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the ſcriptures, thus pronouncing <hi>(lucem inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat inacceſſam) hee dwelleth in a light, to which there is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Timoth. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>no acceſſe.</hi> Here therefore, a periode and a ſtop of this my diſcourſe: not able to make any further progreſſe; I anſwere, (as <hi>Simonides</hi> the Philoſopher did to <hi>Hiero</hi> tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching God) the more I ſeeke the perfections of Chriſt, the leſſe I find them. But for application and vſe of this doctrine; I will make no other then what I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made; by which I ſee Chriſt already in faith, and loue applied to your ſoules: with whom I doubt not, but that you will ſpeake, and commune as Chriſtians ought with ſuch a Chriſt, ſo deere, ſo ſweet, ſo perfect a Spouſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How much more: he blood of Chriſt?</head>
               <p>But how ſhall I proſecure the other conſideration of this my firſt part of my text? what a paradoxe, ſhall I ſeeme to deliuer, to ſpeake of the blood of ſuch a maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty? of ſuch a glory? how ill doe conſort, the maieſty of Godhead; and the humility of bloodſhed? theſe attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of diuinity, and ſuch defects of humanity: ſuch a humility, and ſuch a glory? If I ſhould preach to the Gentiles, they would eſteeme mee <hi>(in ſanire) to bee mad,</hi> and ſuch doctrine to be meere folly: if to the Iewes, they would not indure the ſcandall of the Croſſe; nor the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17743:15"/> of this blood: but conſidering I preach to this ſo religious an aſſembly, called and aſſociated together <hi>(non de ſanguinibus) not by bloods;</hi> not by bloods of Buls, Goates, Sheepe, &amp;c. but <hi>(de ſanguine quaſi agni immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lati) by the one blood of the immaculate Lambe:</hi> one lambe, and once ſacrificed. I ſhall eaſily perſwade you, the ſweet coniunction of ſuch a Maieſtie, and ſuch a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie: I ſhall eaſily perſwade you, that the blood of this lambe is <hi>(virtus Dei omni credenti) the very vertue of God, to euery one who beleeueth,</hi> and confideth in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How much more the blood of Chriſt?</head>
               <p>Manifold is the acception of blood in ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and with prophane Philoſophers. Blood for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, man-ſlaughter, death, crueltie: blood for impuritie, vncleaneneſſe of life: blood for the ſeed of generation: blood, as it is the ſeat and domicile of life; the immediate cauſe and inſtrument of nouriſhment, of motion, of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall health, colour, temperature, due complection, &amp;c. But intermitting all theſe acceptions, and the moralizing vpon them: the blood which our Apoſtle meaneth, is the blood of Chriſt, the Seale of the new Teſtament, the blood of redemption, ſatisfaction; of reconciliation, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification.</p>
               <p>O wonderfull and moſt venerable blood! But is the acception of this blood of our one Ieſus, one, or mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold? It is Chriſtian Catholike Auditors, both one, and manifold: one, in Chriſt: manifold, from Chriſt: one in Chriſt, in an indiuiduall, ſubſtantiall, and integrall vnitie of nature, concurring to make him a perfect liuing man: manifold, as it is effuſed and flowing from Chriſt, to make vs perfect Chriſtian men. How manifold is this blood? witneſſe, firſt, that bloodie ſweat in the garden, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing rather from his tender and inward compaſſion ouer
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17743:15"/> ſinners, then from any deſolation. O droppes, not drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, but of blood <hi>(decurrentis in terram) running downe vpon the earth!</hi> what earth? mankind, by ſinfull conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation transformed into earth: but this blood trickleth, yea runneth downe vpon it, to waſh it, to ſanctifie it, and to make it fructifie. Witneſſe thoſe ſtreames of blood which guſhed from euery part of Chriſts ſacred body, when the mercileſſe ſcourgers whipped and tormented him, being faſt bound to a pillar. I reade elſewhere <hi>(Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus erat petra, &amp; bibebant de ſpirituali conſequente eos</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>petra) Chriſt was a rocke, and they drunke</hi> (the auncient faithfull) <hi>of the ſpirituall rocke which followed them.</hi> Here I contemplate Chriſt, not a rocke, but a moſt tender man, faſt bound to a ſtone, to a rocke, whipped, ſcourged, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, to yeeld forth a ſtreame, a great fountaine of blood; of which all may drinke, from the beginning vntill the conſummation of the world. For not onely (<hi>Agnus occiſus,</hi> but <hi>Agnus flagellatus ab origine mundi</hi>) was the Lambe ſlaine, but alſo whipped, from the beginning of the world: <hi>Moyſes, Abraham, Noe, Adam,</hi> drunke of this rocke, or rather of this Chriſt, bound to a rocke, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a fountaine of blood. Not here (<hi>petra erat Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi>) Chriſt was a rocke, a ſtone, but (<hi>apud Petram Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi>) a tender man, a ſenſitiue man, faſt bound to a ſtone, a pillar of ſtone, feeling the ſharpe paine of moſt cruell ſcourging, able enough to haue killed Chriſt, had he not alſo determined to aſcend vp into the Palme-tree: what ſaid, I the Palme-tree? I ſhould haue ſaid the tree of the croſſe, the tree of curſe, of malediction. Witneſſe, thoſe currents from his head crowned with thornes, his hands and feet nailed and pierced. Witneſse his moſt diuine ſide opened with a ſpeare; whence, in teſtimonie that this Chriſt had made a complete expiation for mankind: with his laſt droppes of blood, water alſo iſsued forth: <hi>(conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuo exiui ſanguis &amp; aqua) preſently,</hi> inſtantly, vpon the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17743:16"/> opening of the ſacred ſide, <hi>blood and water went forth.</hi> Blood and water ſtood attending that opening of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine wall; which once opened, and launced, blood and water, fel not out, ruſhed not out, dropped not out; but went out, walked out, going in fortitude, in vertue, ſtrength, to confront with Satan, to vanquiſh death and damnation, to conſummate our redemption. What mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is this, to vs beleeuing, that this blood and water, by a ſtrange and wonderfull vnion, were vnited to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence and perſon of him, who is the author of all life, giuer of all motion? O blood and water, conſummating all ſanctification, filling all ruines, in heauen and vpon earth! <hi>Waight and ballance are the iudgements of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaith the diuine Scripture.</hi> But in this extraordinarie worke of our redemption, in this iudgement exerciſed vpon the ſonne of God, what meaſure hath beene kept? what ballance hath beene vſed? what meane hath beene obſerued? all is ſhedde, all is effuſed: and in teſtimonie thereof, with the laſt droppes of blood, water is adioyned; by ſuch a coniunction of water with blood, proclaiming to mankind, That the blood of Chriſt doth not onely me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, redeeme, ſatisfie; but alſo waſh, purifie, ſanctifie with puritie of grace, the conſciences of all ſuch, who with a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and a ſanctifying faith ſhould confide in it.</p>
               <p>Rowze vp you ſoules beloued, in this blood, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of me, by which of all theſe bloods are we redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: and I will anſwer vnto you, That wee are redeemed by them all: all theſe are <hi>(paſſio Chriſti) the paſſion of Chriſt:</hi> by them all, by them all: plentifull therefore is your redemption, abſolute, and in very rigour of iuſtice ſo conſummate, that applied by faith to your ſoules, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by faith, (iuſtifying faith, ſanctifying faith I meane, which deſtroyeth dead workes, innouateth your conſciences with a new, and with the principall ſpirit) the ſeuere, and iuſt eye of God cannot reiect or condemne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17743:16"/> ſuch as are ſigned, and marked with the ſame. The laſt houre (Chriſtian hearers) endeth the day, the laſt ſand emptieth the houre-glaſſe, the laſt droppes fill the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, the laſt figure conſummateth and maketh perfect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny number; ſo, the laſt droppes of Chriſts blood, conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, perfected, our redemption. All theſe effuſions of blood by me mentioned, did concurre to your redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſaluation; but the laſt droppes conſummated all: for it is the blood of Chriſt dying, the effuſion of blood, in which the life of Chriſt was offered, which conſummate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfected all, merited, ſatisfied for vs. O moſt ſweet prouidence of God! <hi>(non alius defuit Deo, ſaluandi mundum modus) there wanted not,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner, or meanes to God, for ſauing of the world.</hi> Notwithſtanding, by blood he would haue it done, and this by the blood of his onely begotten ſonne.</p>
               <p>O moſt potent blood, not of Bulles or Goates, for a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and carnall purification onely; but of Chriſt, to make ſuch a purification of ſoules, that the eie of the moſt iuſt Iudge looking vpon them, ſigned with the ſame, cannot repute them vncleane, vnſanctified, but diuinely beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Not of Bulles, and Goates, Calues, and Kiddes, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be repeated, &amp; reiterated: but of one only Chriſt, by one onely oblation eternally ſanctifying all ſincere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers. Not of goates and oxen, for the Iewiſh nation onely; but of Chriſt, the liuing fountaine <hi>(irrigans vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſam terram) watering the whole earth:</hi> all ages, all ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, all conditions of mankind. Foure-fold were the riuers, which iſſued from one fountaine, in the earthly Paradiſe, and watered the whole earth, making the ſame fruitfull: not foure fold onely, but manifold are the riuers, which iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued from the fountaine in the ſpirituall Paradiſe, where Chriſt Ieſus was placed with his ſpouſe, his wife, his Church. How manifold were the riuers, iſſuing from this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17743:17"/> fountaine, you haue already heard, from euery part, ſide, and end of this fountaine, from the head of this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, by thornes; from the feet, and hands by nailes; from his ſweeteſt face, by blowes, buffets, and moſt cruell ſcrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, from his ſide, by the ſpeare; from his whole body, by the ſharpe ſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ging of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> executioners.</p>
               <p>O Rare fountaine, ſtreaming on euery ſide! O diuine altitude, longitude, latitude, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ofundity of this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine! Oh that we would, with all Saints, comprehend the altitude, longitude, latitude, and profoundnes of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eding fountaine of this bleeding Chriſt, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Apoſtle in his Epiſtle to the Epheſians?<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.</note> O that we would, or could endeauour, to comprehend in our daily conſiderations, the altitude of the bleeding head of this fountaine? ſhould we not, trow yee, with teares of ſorrow, and compunction, bewaile the pride, of our owne ambitious heads? ſhould we not waſh away our aſpiring thoughts, by which yeerely, lately, at all moments, we proiect our owne greatneſſe, to mount vp ourſelues, though it bee with the circumuention of our owne brethren, breach of fidelity, incurring of periurie, and the commitment of any moſt dreadfull ſinnes? Oh that wee would conſider, the longitude of this bleeding fountaine? longitude in time, from thurſday euening, till friday euening; for vpon friday euening (<note place="margin">Mar. 15.</note>
                  <hi>Circa horam nonam expirauit Ieſus</hi>) about the <hi>ninth houre ſweet Ieſus expired:</hi> I ſhould haue ſaid, longitude in time, from the day of his circumciſion, vntill his expiration, or rather vntill the apertion of his ſide, after his expiring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Longitude</hi> in place, from the Garden of <hi>Gethſemanie</hi> vnto the houſes of <hi>Annas, Caiaphas;</hi> thence to the towne houſe; thence to the mount Caluary; where wee haue many longitudes; longitudes of his armes, ſtretched out to the armes of the Croſſe; longitude of his feet, and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proportioned to the length of the Croſſe, and in all theſe longitudes, Chriſt boiſterouſly drawne out, ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17743:17"/> forth, mercileſly hoyſed vp, immanely pitched downe with the croſſe, faſtened in the ground; what a mouing? what an effectuall and diuine longitude would this proue, if it were daily meditated vpon? would it not (thinke you) produce in our ſoules a longanimity of patience, in all our tribulations? a longitude of hope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuggeſtions of diſpaire? a length of loue, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our enemies, offending and iniuring vs, though neuer ſo often? A vertue very neceſſary, and needfull in theſe times, eſpecially, with our Gallants; who ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly ſtand vpon their points of honour; who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer as yet haue learned, for Chriſts ſake, to forgiue any wrong; to put vp any iniury vpon any ſubmiſſion, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement whatſoeuer: nothing will content them; but (<hi>lex Talionis</hi>) the law of requitall, of equality: An eie, for an eie; a tooth for a tooth: life for life, blood for blood? O yee Chriſtians! (truly Gallants, and truly nobles, if you heare this leſſon) in the behalfe of this Chriſt; which did once ſuſteine your perſons, to deliuer you from damnation; who ſuffered ſo many iniuries, to giue you eternall honour: I aske of you, I require of you, that for his ſake, for his loue, for his honour, and for the honour of the Chriſtian name, end your controuerſies, conclude your contentions, and quarrels as Chriſtians ought to doe: that is ſo often, (<hi>though ſeuenty ſeuen times</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> ſaith Chriſt) as the offender ſhall acknowledge his fault, make ſubmiſſion; doe ye forgiue, be reconciled, forget in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries.</p>
               <p>I dare here boldly pronounce, he vnderſtandeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, he knoweth nothing, he is worth nothing; he hath no dramme of Chriſtian magnanimitie in him; who will not admit, and approue ſuch a reconcilement, to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, honourable, glorious, both before God and man: ſuch a reconcilement (I ſay) as the duty of a Chriſtian to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17743:18"/> Chriſt crucified, dead and ſacrificed, requireth, challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, commandeth. And if any here will deſpiſe, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this Chriſtian counſell, and ſtand vpon Machiuillian, and Italian <hi>puntidel-honore,</hi> I will confidently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt him, or them, whatſoeuer they be, that of the Prophet <hi>Oſee, (Ventum ſeminat, turbinem metet) he ſoweth a wind, but ſhall reape a whirlewind?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oſec. 8.</note> he ſoweth a puffe of vaine glory, a blaſt of ſpaniſh Oſtentation, but ſhall reape a whirle wind of confuſion and ignominie to himſelfe and his poſterity, perhaps in this liue, if he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the law, and feele the ſeuerity of the ſame, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as he deſerueth) or elſe moſt aſſuredly at the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of his iudgement, he ſhall meet with that dreadfull whirlewind of (<hi>Ito maledicte) Depart thou accurſed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> which ſhall conuolue and wrap him vp with his conſorts, the ſeruants of the Roaring and deuouring Lion, into the whirlepoole of Eternall damnation, where, and with whom, he may if it ſhall ſo pleaſe him, caſt firebrands, for precedency of honour, and chaires of dignitie eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie.</p>
               <p>But to our ſountaine, to our fountaine. Oh that wee would conſider Chriſt with ſuch a length of his armes, ſo prodigallie and charitably effuſing, and powring forth his blood, to waſh all, to ſanctifie all: would it not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs, to lengthen forth our armes, and to open our palmes to the poore, and needy? but out alas, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template not this longitude, and therefore inſteed of ſtretching forth our armes to the poore, we ſtretch and whet our tongues, we ſharpen our ſpeeches againſt them, we ad affliction to their affliction, we reuile, exprobrate, diſcomfort them. O damnable cuſtome ouerflowing <hi>Italy!</hi> O wretched practiſe ouerabounding <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France!</hi> O practiſe of Reprobates, too too frequent in <hi>England.</hi> O faſhion euery where in faſhion, and yet the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17743:18"/> faſhion only, of Reprobates and children of perdition! I boldly here ſpeake it, that it is a ſpeciall ſigne, marke, badge, and character of reprobates, and children of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſo to en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertaine, ſo to abuſe the poore <hi>Lazars;</hi> why ſaid I poore <hi>Lazars?</hi> I ſhould haue ſaid poore Chriſts, and poore Ieſus in theſe <hi>Lazars:</hi> Hee hath ſaid it, and I dare proclaime it, <hi>whatſoeuer you ſhall doe to one of theſe, you ſhall doe to me.</hi> Honourable, worſhipfull and<note place="margin">Mat 25.</note> moſt worthy Chriſtians, eſpecially you of the deuout and religious ſex, who are more accuſtomed to be like to the worthy Matron of your owne ſex deſcribed in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, <hi>to open her palmes to the needy, and to ſtretch forth her armes to the poore:</hi> I beſeech you often to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider<note place="margin">Prouerb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> of this blood of Chriſt, ſhed ſo prodigally for your ſoules: and if you will not be prodigall to him in his poore, at leaſt be liberall, be Charitable: Expend of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that ſaying of Chriſt to the couteous Scribes, which I now inclucate to your religious eares and hearts, (<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te elemoſynam &amp; ecce omnia munda ſunt vobis:) Giue almes, and behold all things are cleane vnto you:</hi> Be chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> be liberall, be prodigall, vnto the poore <hi>Lazars,</hi> vnto the needie Chriſts, and <hi>behold all things ſhall bee cleane vnto you:</hi> if you doe not, beware of the thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clap (<hi>depart accurſed,</hi>)<note place="margin">Mat 25.</note> the which, as aſſuredly as the word of God ſhall not paſſe vnfulfilled, ſo certainely ſhall all ſuch as decline their eares from hearing, and their hearts from comforting and releeuing the poore, ſhall heare it, ſhall vndergoe it, and ſhal be eternally confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with it.</p>
               <p>But from the length of this fountaine, to the breadth, to the latitude thereof, the which if wee would deuoutly conſider, yeelding ſtreames of blood on euery ſide, and vpon all ſorts of perſons, vpon enemies, and onely ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all enemies, to what a breadth of loue would it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17743:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17743:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17743:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17743:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17743:21"/> perſwade vs? to loue all that Chriſt loueth: and becauſe Chriſt loueth, to loue our friendes in Chriſt, and our enemies for Chriſt. What a latitude of reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would it ingender in our Soules, to walke the commandements of God cheerefully? what a breadth of charitable loue and compaſſion would it cauſe in vs, to giue to the poore cheerefully? for (<hi>hilarem da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem diligit Deus) God loueth a merry and cheerefull gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor 2.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>Would we conſider the profunditie of this fountaine, founded in loue, and the meſtimable charitie of God; founded in the vnſpeakable humilitie of the ſonne of God: what a depth of humilitie, what a profoundneſſe of meekeneſſe, what an <hi>abyſſe</hi> of charitie, what a purpoſe of ſtedfaſt perſeuerance in Gods ſeruice, would it inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and confirme in our mindes? Let experience, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Hearers, be your miſtreſle in this: make triall, and as you find, ſo be perſwaded, ſo giue credit to what I ſpeake.</p>
               <p>But alas! who can bewaile ſufficiently, the miſeries of theſe times? Euen as in the earthly Paradiſe, after the deluge of the ſlood had ouerwhelmed the whole world, neither the fountaine, nor the riuers iſſuing from the ſame, can certamely be diſtinguiſhed, or knowne, which, or where they are: ſo out alas! ſince partly, deepe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Poperie, manifold inundation of hereſie, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of iniquitie, extreame defect of charitie, haue ouerwhelmed the viſible face of the Church; it is hard to finde, where this fountaine of Chriſt crucified, where theſe riuers iſſuing from the ſame fountaine, doe make their courſes, where their channels be. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Chriſtians, I ſpeake not this, as though I knew no place where Chriſt crucified is truely preached: for in ſo ſpeaking, I ſhould calumniate that Church, to which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17743:21"/> I haue happily aſſociated my ſelfe, where the infinite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergie, vertue of Chriſts death, and paſſion, is daily and inceſſantly preached, commended, extolled, and applied to all beleeuing ſoules. But I ſpeake this of Chriſtian conferences, of deuoute ſoules, who ſhould daily meditate, and ſucke of this fountaine; who by their pure liues, and ſincere conuerſations ſhould ſhew, that it is the blood of the moſt immaculate Lambe, whereof they drinke: it is the blood of the vnſpotted ſacrifice, where with they are fedde and nouriſhed. Such kind of channels, ſuch kind of ſtreames are hardly ſound, are hardly ſcene. But let vs yet at laſt awake our ſoules, and recall them from drinking of the puddles of Egypt: there is no houre too late for repentance, the energie of this blood is euerlaſting it ſpeaketh ſtill better, and lowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to all, then that of <hi>Abel:</hi> therefore euen now, and at this moment, it will not be too late to beginne to drinke of this fountaine; no impuritie ſo great, the which it wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth not away: it is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of vocation, iuſtification, ſanctification, perſeuerance, glorification; becauſe the blood of the Eternall <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of all things.</p>
               <p>O Well of all conſolation! O fountaine of all Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces! O wounds not killing, but the onely <hi>Aſyle</hi> and Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatie of ſinnefull and afflicted ſoules! wounds, in which, and in which only, we may be ſecured from the ſting of ſinne, and power of Satan.</p>
               <p>Giue me leaue here for this purpoſe, to apply to your eares, the words of a certaine deuout Father: <hi>Vbi tuta</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>ſirmaque requies infirmis, &amp;c. Where is there ſafe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure reſt to the infirme and weake, but in the wounds of our Sauiour? there I dwell more ſecurely, by how much he is more potent to ſaue: the world fretteth, my fleſh preſſeth, Satan lieth in waite; I fall not, becauſe I am founded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17743:22"/> a firme rocke: I haue ſinned a great ſinne, my conſcience will be troubled, but it ſhall not be ouer-troubled, becauſe I will remember the wounds of the Lord: for hee is woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for our iniquities: What ſo neere to death, which is not ſaucd by his death? If therefore ſo potent, and ſo efficient a medicine ſhall come into my minde, I cannot be terrified with the greatneſſe of any diſeaſe.</hi> And againe a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>But I doe confidently vſurpe to mee, what is wanting to me, from the bowels of my Lord, which abound with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Neither doe there want holes, by which it may flowe out, they haue digged his hands and feete, and haue pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his ſide with a launce: and by theſe chinkes, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to ſncke honnis from the rocke, and oyle from the moſt hard ſtone, and taſte, that the Lord is moſt ſweet. The ſecrets of the heart are opened by the holes of the body, that great Sacrament of pietie is opened: The bowels of mercie of our God, in which the Orient from aboue hath viſited vs, are opened. And why may not bowels appeare, and ſhewe themſelues, by, and through wounds? In what more cleerely, then in thy wounds, doth it appeare, O Lord? that thou art ſweete, meeke, and of much mercy: for greater mercy no man hath, then that hee giue his life for his friend: but thou, O Lord, haſt had greater chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, who haſt giuen thy ſelfe for off-caſts and damned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Therefore my merit is the mercie of the Lord: I am not altogether voyd of merit, ſo long as he ſhall not be voyd of mercie and miſerations. But if the mercies of our Lord, be many, euen ſo am I much in merits: for what if I am guiltie to my ſoule of many ſinnes? truely, where ſinnes haue abounded, grace hath ouer-abounded. And if the mercies of the Lord be from eternitie to eternitie, I alſo wil for all eternities ſing his mercies.</hi> And a little after: <hi>How great in the holes of the rocke is the multitude of weetneſſe, the fulneſſe of grace, the perfection of vertues?</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17743:22"/> Thus farre deuout <hi>Bernard.</hi> Truely great, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry delectable is the ſweetneſſe of theſe woundes, honie in the mouth, melodie in the eares, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultation in the heart; from diſcourſing whereof I am moſt loath to ſurceaſe: but my Text calleth mee away.</p>
               <p>As for vſe and application of this Doctrine, I make no other, then that which your religious hearts haue made already, by your conſtant faith in it, by your inflamed affections of loue to it. But before I proceed to my other parts of my Text, giue mee leaue to giue a glaunce at the Popiſh abomination, ſet vp by humane inuention, againſt the moſt dreadfull ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of this blood of the croſſe. Let vs pauſe a little.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How much more the blood of Chriſt?</head>
               <p>The Pontificians and Romaniſts, who out of a Phariſaicall pride, haue accurſed and condemned all the Reformed Churches; for the ſetting forth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling the Maieſtie, and efficacie of this blood: and of the infinite energie of the one and onely ſacrifice, and daily oblation of the Chriſtians: haue withall, by their moſt prophane and idolatrous ſacrifice of their Maſſe, (againſt which, I haue more largely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſed out of their owne Canons, in my Booke of Motiues) as much as lieth in them, conculcated the blood of the New Teſtament, and prophaned the one and onely ſacrifice of the croſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antiochus</hi> was a figure of Antichriſt, hee tooke away and aboliſhed for his time, the daily ſacrifice of the Iewes. The Romane Antichriſt (Romane Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſt I call him, for we muſt vnderſtand, that there haue beene, are, and ſhall bee, Antichriſts of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent kindes) hath by might and maine, oppugned the onely ſacrifice of the croſſe, although with many faire pretences, he would ſeeme to magnifie the ſame in his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17743:23"/> Maſſing ſacrifice: but alas, how vainely? Briefly, let vs conſider, the Chriſtians ſacrifice of the croſſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as it is an expiation for ſinne, or a ſatisfaction for puniſhment, a meanes of reconcilement, a merit of ſaluation, a powerfull deliuerance from Satan; and we ſhall finde, that in all theſe reſpects, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (not now to be ſtood vpon) that the man of Sin, and his Diſciples, haue moſt abhominably depraued, prophaned, contemned it.</p>
               <p>The ſacrifice of the croſſe, being of an immenſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and infinite efficacie: <hi>Chriſt the high Prieſt, by one onely oblation of it, in the conſummation of the world, appeared for the deſtruction of ſinne,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the ninth Chapter to the Hebrewes, and the 26. verſe, adding in the very next verſe, thus: (<hi>Et quemadmodum) And euen as it is appointed, for man once to die, and after followeth iudgement:</hi> ſo Chriſt <hi>was once offered, to take away the ſinnes of many.</hi> And ſo frequent are the paſſages of holy Scripture, for Chriſts once offering himſelfe, by once ſhedding of his blood, and for his one oblation onely, and once one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be made; that it is altogether needleſſe to adde more, for the confirmation of ſo euident a truth. The Aduerſaries themſelues cannot denie it, though to their owne confuſion: for by their new daily conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratings of Chriſt, I ſhould ſay, their daily new makings productions, factions, creations, and <hi>fieries</hi> of Chriſt, they are confounded. In ſuch wordes and phraſes they delight, and ſuch wordes their Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation requireth: for it is impoſſible to conceiue a ſubſtantiall Tranſubſtantiation, without a ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all production, making, faction, or <hi>fierie</hi> of that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, into which the other ſubſtance which is deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is tranſubſtantiated, &amp; ſubſtantially conuerted. And this is ſo manifeſt, in the very principles of all Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17743:23"/> that the learnedſt of them cannot denie it: and yet, it is impoſſible, and implieth, that Chriſt, who was, and is ſubſtantially ſubſiſtent, before all their conſecrations, ſhould be by the ſame, ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally produced, made, created: for, a ſubſtantiall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction and making, is the bringing, and drawing out of a ſubſtance; from a no being, to a being; from <hi>a non eſſe,</hi> to an <hi>eſſe;</hi> from a no exiſtence, to an exiſtence: how then is it conceiueable, that Chriſts ſubſtance, which was, and is before their conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhould be made, and produced by the ſame? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it is vnconceiueable, that there ſhould be a new production of any ſubſtance, or Perſon, and perfect ſuppoſit, without the making of a new ſubſiſtence, or exiſtence: Tell me then, O all ye Pontificians, what new ſubſiſtences? what new exiſtencies are made of one Chriſt, by your productiue, creatiue, and factiue conſecrations in your maſſing fiue words? But were theſe daily, and infinitely multiplied conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations, productions, reall offerings, reall deſitions, ceſſations, remoouings, deſtructions of Chriſt vpon your Altars, in your ſtomakes, poſſible, as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and beleeue; yet, by them all, it is manifeſt, and as cleare as the Sunne, that you reſt not in the one, and only reall ſacrifice of the croſſe; but that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire daily new reall offerings, conſecratings of Chriſt vpon your altars. And can any one of them, be ſo impudently ignorant, as to affirme, that the conſecrations, oblations, conſumptions, deſitions of Chriſt, which they make daily, and multiply infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely vpon their prophane altars, and in their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, ſhould be the ſame in number, and indiuidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vnity, with the making of Chriſt in his mothers wombe? with that offering of Chriſt, that conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; death of Chriſt, vpon the croſſe? with that reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb facs="tcp:17743:24"/> of Chriſt from the Sepulcher? Beleeue me, Chriſtian and Catholike Hearers, when it is deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of them whether their ſacrifice, oblation, making, and conſumption of Chriſt, be the ſame in indiuiduall vnity, and number with that, vpon the croſſe, they are ſo puſled, to ſolue the knot, that they know not, what to anſwere; Sometimes, they will ſay, it is the ſame in number, and indiuiduall vnity. (I meane, as it is a ſacrifice, an oblation, and offering,) with that of the croſſe: but who would not ſcorne this? who would not contemne ſuch ignorant folly? the abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the paradox, ouerthroweth it ſelfe: for there, Chriſt was truly, and naturallie borne, by a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall generation from his mother; here, by an imagined ſubſtantiall action, and <hi>fieri,</hi> of their owne, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth nothing, which was not before, and that, which is already made, in one place, by one ſubſtantiall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is impoſſible, that it ſhould be made often by many other ſubſtantiall actions in other places, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we will make many things ſubſtantially to be one, and one to be many ſubſtantially: which inſoldeth contradiction, as all Philoſophers will eaſily grant: There, Chriſts blood was truly and really ſhed, here in imagination, and ſeeming onely, as themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe: there, his body was truly rent: here, onely in ſhew: there, Chriſt truly died, and ſo really, that (<hi>in triduo) in thoſe three daies,</hi> whileſt his body lay in the graue, he was not man: (for ſuch a diſſolution, ſuch a ſeparation of the ſoule of Chriſt, from his body, which true death requireth was neceſſary for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,) here, he only ceaſeth to be, (as they vnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligibly teach) by an imaginary ceſſation in their box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, pixes, ſtomackes, when their ſpecies, their formes of bread, and wine, as whiteneſſe, roundneſſe, ſauour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, doe ceaſe, are corrupted, and changed.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:17743:24"/>
               <p>Some others therefore pretending more learning than wiſedome, or Chriſtian pietie; grant indeed, that there is not the ſame indiuiduall, and numerall oblation of Chriſt, vpon their Altars, with that of the Croſſe: which their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere indeed is moſt true, according to their owne princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, both in Philosophie, and Diuinitie; but diſcouereth the ignominie of their abhomination, in ſetting vp, and teaching a new daily, reall ſacrificing, and oblation of their imagined Chriſt vpon their Altars; againſt that infinitely valuable offering, and ſacrificing of Chriſt Ieſus vpon the Croſſe: by which once only, really, truly, corporally, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally offered, all faithfull beleeuers are iuſtified, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, are conſummated, by the eternall might and neuer dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing energie of his bloud. I pretermit here, to ſtand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of them, why they doe ſo vainly require a reall and truly Propitiatorie ſacrifice of Chriſt, in Perſon, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, vpon their Altars; to apply the vertue of Chriſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed vpon the Croſſe: for how vaine is it to imagine, that the ſame cannot be applied by a liuely faith, and the vſe of a holy Sacrament of Bread and Wine, as it is applied by Faith and Water in Baptiſme? I pretermit to charge them, that they are not yet accorded what to affirme, or how to teach, in what action of their Maſſe, this their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice doth conſiſt, whether in their making of Chriſt by their Prieſts fiue mightie wordes; or by their Eleuation of their Chriſt vp, or by their laying downe of their Chriſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their Altars; theſe thinges I omit, with much more to like purpoſe, becauſe the out-running of time cauſeth me to be briefe.</p>
               <p>But you know Chriſtian and Catholike Auditors, that they (not without cauſe) contend for this their reall, and vnbloudy ſacrificing of their Chriſt; as for the very liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſoule of their religion: you are not ignorant, how many zelouſe and renowned Profeſſors of the only bloud of the Croſſe, haue and doe daily ſhed their blouds, for the denying of their prophane ſacrifice: doubtleſſe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17743:25"/> then they doe, greatly magnifie it; they doe greatly extoll it: Heare me how; and firſt, touching the expiation, and remiſſion of ſinne, I will deliuer vnto you, a poſition, or rather a Paradoxe of theirs (for ſo I am aſſured it will ſeeme vnto you.) Notwithſtanding this their faith of their Chriſt, truly and really ſacrificed in their Maſſe, yet they doe denie power, valour, and efficacie to this their ſacrifice, to take away the ſinnes of ſuch as doe offer it, or of ſuch, for whom it is offered; what ſaid I, that they denie this their ſacrifice to expiate the ſinnes of the offerers, or for whom it is offered? I ſo ſaid indeede, and it is moſt true: but yet they grant vnto it forſooth, force, and energie, to aboliſh, to wipe away ſmaller ſinnes, veniall ſinnes; ſuch as are alſo taken away by their holy Bread; by their ſprinkling of aſhes vpon Aſhwedneſday; by their daily luſtrall, prophane holy water; by their knocking of their breaſts; by their Prieſts bleſſings; by their ſigning of themſelues with the ſigne of the Croſſe; by bearing of Palmes vpon Palme-Sunday; and Candells vpon Candle-maſſe-day; and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable ſuch their ſacramentalls, (deuiſed by humane preſumption) as themſelues teach, and confeſſe. Whereby it is manifeſt, that they doe equalize the ſprinkling of their luſtrall water, of their prophane aſhes, in the effect of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of veniall ſmaller ſinners, with the true and reall offering of their Chriſt, their God and Man, ſacrificed, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon their Altars. O moſt prophane, moſt ignorant folly of theſe men! their Chriſt and God, truly offered as a propitiatorie ſacrifice for ſinnes by them; and being the very ſame with that of the Croſſe; for expiating of ſinnes, doth no more, worketh, effecteth, no more than the baſe, ſeruile, contemptible aſhes of a few Palmes, magically by them conſecrated vpon Palme-Sunday, and ſprinkled vpon their counterfeit humiliats vpon Aſhwedneſday. But to proceede, heare yet ſomewhat, as prodigious as the former, if not more. If either Prieſt, or Lay perſon, wanting opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of a Ghoſtly Father, to confeſſe their ſecret ſinnes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17743:25"/> vnto; ſhall with a moſt contrite heart lamenting, &amp; bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their ſinnes, acknowledging them, confeſſing them to God, offer, or receiue this their ſacrifice, with ſuch a liuing faith, and humble deuotion, as they require; yet this their Chriſt and God, there ſo offered as a ſacrifice Propitiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, there ſo receiued as their diuine Sacrament, doth not ſanctifie the conſcience, doth not expiate the ſinne of the conſciences of ſuch Offerers, of ſuch Receiuers of it, as it is a ſacrifice, or as it is a Sacrament; but, as it is ioyned withall, with an implicite and vertuall purpoſe, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the offerers, of the receiuers, to confeſſe their ſinnes to ſome approued Prieſt, ſome Ghoſtly Father: and if there be any Papall or Epiſcopall reſeruation (a cuſtome, a moſt deteſtable cuſtome, very frequent amongſt them) then forſooth, the vertuall and implicit vow muſt bee to confeſſe to ſuch Biſhops, to the holy Father, and haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly abſolution from them, or elſe, this their Chriſt, as a propitiatorie Sacrifice, expiateth not their ſinnes, as a diuine Sacrament ſanctifieth not their conſciences. O moſt blaſphemous doctrine, eneruating the bloud of Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed only to ſet vp the Papall Soueraigntie, and their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian pride, to the horrible ruine and inconſolable af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of innumerable ſoules! O moſt blaſphemous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and damnable follie rather than hereſie! The bloud of Chriſt truly offered, truly receiued, by ſoules confeſſing ſinne to God, lamenting ſinne for the loue of God; cannot, doth not aboliſh ſinne, without implicite relation, to a Papall abſolution; if it ſhall pleaſe his Holineſſe, to reſtrain ſuch ſinnes, to reſerue ſuch caſes for his owne abſolution, and not without ſome pecuniarie mulcts, as the practiſe <hi>(Romanae Curiae, &amp; taxe, Apoſtolicae Cancellariae.) Of the Roman Court, and the taxe, of the Apoſtolicall Chancerie</hi> do euince. Catholike and religious Hearers, what can bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted impious doctrine, againſt the only ſacrifice of the Croſſe, if this be not to be eſteemed; to bee accounted for ſuch?</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17743:26"/>
               <p>To proceede; As touching the ſatisfaction for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne: Good God! their Altar-ſacrifice is weaker than their fatuouſe Purgatorie-fire, than their vaine Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merian Indulgences (in the founding the treſurie whereof, although Chriſt be the principall, yet he hath his conſorts and fellowes, Saint <hi>Stephens,</hi> Saint <hi>Laurences, &amp;c.</hi> to ſet vp and inrich their vaine checker) for theſe forſooth, can take away and ſatisfie, by the way of Iuſtice, of perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital and repaiment for all puniſhment remaining and due to ſinne: Yea further, the profeſſion and ſolemne vow of a Monaſticall life, in the handes and preſence of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours of ſuch houſes, Monaſteries, Nunries, is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate and perfect expiating of all puniſhment for ſinne, as abſolute as Baptiſme it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>But their Chriſt offered in their Maſſe, as it is a ſacrifice, doth not this, effecteth not this; neither in the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, nor in them, for whome it is offered, nor in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers. What ſaid I? doth it not ſo? yes but it doth: I haue forgotten my ſelfe, I confeſſe it: it doth ſatisfie for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; but when? but when? Marry, when this their Chriſt is offered and ſacrificed vpon priuiledged Altars, as at Loretto, at Sichem, at S. <hi>Laurences,</hi> at S. <hi>Sebaſtians</hi> without the Gates of Rome: then, then; and vpon ſuch Altars, by the holy Father of Rome, priuiledged for ſuch ends: Chriſt ſacrificed, doth, and can ſatisfie for all puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne; then he can worke a plenarie Indulgence, and deliuerie of ſoule vpon ſoule, out of Purgatorie: Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when this their Chriſt is offered and ſacrificed by En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Prieſts in this Kingdome, vpon Wedneſdaies, and Fridaies; prouided they haue a ſanctified Medall, or Croſſe for that purpoſe, bleſſed by their holy Father, either with them, or lying vpon their Altar: then forſooth, vpon ſuch an indulgent Indulgence, from the moſt prophane Baron of the Roman Checker, Chriſt can, and doth ſatisfie for the puniſhment and paine due to ſin: how poore? how weak? how contemptible is their altar Chriſt? their maſſe ſacrifice?
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17743:26"/> which needeth the addition of ſuch an Indulgencer, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for the paine and puniſhment of ſinne? weaker, and feebler, is this ſacrifice, then their Ordinarie Prieſts, with their bleſſed Graines, of which ſome bring into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome Decades of thouſands, for ſo many thouſands of ſoules, to deliuer them from all paine of ſinne inioyned, or to bee inioyned (by ghoſtly Fathers) or to bee endured in Purgatorie. But as for the powerfull Friers, Monkes, and Ignatians (called Ieſuites, but haue not a dramme of Ieſus his ſpirit in them) they forſooth, in their very Perſons; and knotted girdels ſurpaſſe this their Chriſt, this their Propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorie Sacrifice: for whoſoeuer ſhall make a firſt confeſſion<note place="margin">Plenarie In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and a generall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don annexed to the very perſons of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnatians and Monkes at the firſt reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any man by them to the Roman Church.</note> of all his ſinnes (which they call a reconcilement from he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie to the Church of Rome) to any of them, ſhall preciſely in that reſpect, not becauſe they are Prieſts, (for ſo euery Prieſt ſhould haue it) for confeſſing firſt to them, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing abſolution from them, haue, and obtaine a full Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie: moſt full, moſt plenarie Indulgence, of all paines and puniſhment due to ſinne.</p>
               <p>How ambitious is this humour of Ignatians, of Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctine but vnbenedict Monks, for Precedencie before their Secular Prieſts, in ſo high a priuiledge and preeminencie of their Perſons? but rather, how impious and deteſtable a practiſe is this, of the Roman Sinagogue, not to equalize only, but to preferre the Perſons of weake men before, and aboue the Perſon of their Chriſt, of their God of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, offered, ſacrificed vpon their Propitiatorie Altars? how myſticall euery knot of their Saint <hi>Francis</hi> his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full girdells are, it is ſuperuacaneous to deliuer; Weare it next your skinne or ſhirt you haue ſuch a pardon: weare it longer, greater is your pardon; pray vpon all the knots, maruailous are your pardons: you ſhal die no ſodain death. O fopperies! Concerning reconcilement to God, mediation to God: Alas, neither Chriſt in their Maſſe, nor vpon the croſſe is with them ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Hear the Remiſts the deprauers<note place="margin">Annotat. in 1. ad Tim. 2.</note> of al youth, in their deprauations vpon the firſt of <hi>Timothie,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17743:27"/> (Opus eſt Mediatore, ad Mediatorem, nec nobis alia eſt vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior, Maria) We haue neede of a Mediator, to our Mediator, and none more profitable, then Marie.</hi> I acknowledge, that they cite theſe words, as out of deuout <hi>Bernard;</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what I haue related out of him here aboue, and how contrarie this their vaine poſition is, to his doctrine, I cannot but thinke that the workes of that learned man are corrupted, and depraued: but howſoeuer (<hi>Bernardus non vidit omnia</hi>) eſpecially in that corrupt and moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant age: And the doctrine is ſo impious, ſo hereticall, that if all <hi>Auſtens,</hi> all <hi>Bernards,</hi> all <hi>Gregories,</hi> all <hi>Angells</hi> from heauen ſhould affirme it, we were to denounce vnto them the Anatheme of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Galathians. For, if they vnderſtand this their poſition of ſuppoſed and abſolute neceſſitie, becauſe ſo appointed by God, that we muſt needes haue a Mediatour to our Mediatour, or elſe that in reſpect of our owne vnworthineſſe, and ſinnes, wee muſt needes haue a Mediatour to our Mediatour, it is the moſt blaſphemous hereſie that euer was maintained, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be perſecuted with fire and fagot, for it ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the whole worke of our Redemption; and I doe bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here pronounce, agreeing to ſacred Scriptures, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of all ancient Churches; that whoſoeuer defendeth ſuch neceſſitie of a Mediatour to our Mediatour, he is fallen from Chriſt, he is fallen from Grace, and ought not to bee eſteemed, named, or called a Chriſtian. As for you Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Auditors, it is ſufficient, and abundantly ſufficient, that you haue an Aduocate, a Redeemer, a Sauiour: An Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate of their Aduocates and Aduocateſſes: a Sauiour of their Sauiours and Sauioureſſes: a Redeemer of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemereſſes, who inuiteth, exhorteth, yea commandeth, <hi>All that are heauy loaden, and labour vnder the burthen of ſinne,</hi> to come vnto him, promiſing that hee will refreſh them, comfort them, &amp;c. But as for ſuch as are diffident in his promiſes, doubtfull of his mercies, diſtruſtfull of his gratious admittance; let them keep themſelues ſtill to their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17743:27"/> Sauioureſſes and Aduocateſſes; which as is manifeſt, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare them, but by the appointment, power, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of him, who commandeth vs, with all confidence to approch to him with <hi>a firme faith, a full truſt to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Heb. 10. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>the holies,</hi> euen vnto himſelfe <hi>our high Prieſt,</hi> and only Sheep-heard of our ſoules. I muſt be briefe.</p>
               <p>As touching the merit of ſaluation, deliuerance from Satans power; which wee Catholike Chriſtians confeſſe, and profeſſe to be only, and effectually through the power of the death and bloud of Ieſus Chriſt vpon the Croſſe: I ſhould trifle the time (which I ſee is ouer-ſpent) if I ſhould ſtand to ſhew how by their confidence and truſt in their Vowes, Pilgrimages, Inuocations to fellow-Seruants: How by their Agnus-Deies, the very excrements of Satan; their idle Relikes, wooden Croſſes, Images, luſtrall Water, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Salt, Palmes, Candles, they doe daily and infinitely derogate from the might &amp; power of the bloud of Chriſt, once crucified: putting more, or at leaſt equall affiance in ſuch deuiſed trumperies (I dare call Croſſes and Images trumperics, if adored, if worſhipped, otherwiſe not) as in the bloud of Chriſt, as in their very Chriſt ſacrificed vpon their Maſſe-Altars, that herein I doe not belie them, it is as manifeſt as Noon daie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for they will not hold nor account him a good Roman Catholike, who doth not vſe, practiſe, eſteeme, and put affiance in them; againſt Fire, Water, Deuill, and all the power of that damned crew. And how cleare it is, that more priuiledged Altars, and Pilgrimages, for ſafetie, for deliuerance; more frequent oblations for helpe and aſſiſtance, are made by the Papiſtically ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and allowed by their Biſhops and Prieſts, vnto their Saints, and vnto the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> then vnto God, then to Chriſt, our only ſacrifice? I know ſome here in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, but I may not name them, who often, frequently, and confidently will ſet vp in their gardens, orchards, gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries, chambers, cloſets, certaine ſmall wooden pictures, framed like to that of Sichem, and there they will make of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17743:28"/> Pilgrimages to the ſame euery day, to obtaine deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſome grieuous dangers and diſaſters: but alas, as yet they haue not been heard; they haue not been holpen. Worthy obſeruing is that ſuperſtitious deuotion vſed long agoe at Canterburie, and at the ſhrine of <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> where the offerings and oblations made to him in a very large degree, yea by ten degrees and more, exceeded the like, made to the euer bleſſed Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and thoſe which were made to her, in a greater degree ſurpaſſed thoſe which were offered and conſecrated to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the one and only Sauiour, and ſacrifice of all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Chriſtians. No man, Catholike hearers, can better te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie how weake their confidence and truſt is in Chriſt and his bloud, than ſuch, as haue beene acquainted with their miſerable miſeries, or rather ſeruile miſeries, and inconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable worſhips. Wherein (beleeue me, moſt worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours) what with their vaine confidence in vnſound In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, their imperfect and ſtained merits, their abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and compleat numbering of all their ſinnes, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances changing the nature of ſinne in their auricular confeſſions (a matter morally impoſſible) the deuouter ſexe amongſt them, or rather the more ſuperſtitious ſexe, leade ſuch inconſolable liues, that any compaſſiue mind and heart knowing the ſame, cannot but compaſſionate their wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and vncomfortable ſeruitudes: no maruaile of this, ſeeing they <hi>ſerue Gods, who cannot, giue them reſt by day nor</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Icrem. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>by night,</hi> ſuch as the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> hath long agoe fore mentioned.</p>
               <p>But thou, O England! reioyce, for that thou art deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from theſe impure Idolatries, and Romiſh ſlaueries; and that the light of Chriſt crucified is illuminated ouer thee, that thou <hi>maieſt ſerue him without feare:</hi> but reioycing<note place="margin">Luc. 1.</note> remember through what meanes the Iewes were cut off, and fell; <hi>through their incredulitie:</hi> and how fell they into<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> incredulitie? becauſe they were <hi>not permanent in goodneſſe,</hi> in workes of ſanctification. Remember how the Romans
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17743:28"/> were cut off? Through <hi>incredulitie:</hi> and how fell they into that? Becauſe they <hi>did not abide in goodneſſe,</hi> and workes of ſanctitie: This is that, which our Apoſtle affirmeth of the Iewes, and threatneth to the Romanes, in the 12 Chapter of his Epiſtle, directed to them, Reade it. Reioyce, O En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, (to make a little digreſſion here, to another kinde of blood) that thou art deliuered from the Papall tyrant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; but reioycing, bee ſtill watchfull, againſt this ambitious Monarch; this moſt bloody Biſhop; <hi>The deuill is a buſie Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> ſaith the old prouerbe, I may ſay, <hi>that this Biſhop, is a buſie deuill, againſt the Church and State of this Kingdome.</hi> This proud Biſhop, hath prophaned the blood of the croſſe, he hath ſet vp his prophane, and his imaginarie blood of his Idolatrous altars: But what? proceedeth hee no further? medleth he with no other blood? Oh that it were ſo! Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is well acquainted, with his proceedings, what they haue beene, and how that in theſe later times, there haue beene no bloody Commotions, and horrible Maſſacres, in which the Holy Fathers fingers haue not beene. And what, O yee Britaines? (for ſo I will call you, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your late happie deliuerie, when as Engliſh, you ſhould haue beene ruinated and deſtroyed; but as Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines for the fauour of your GOD ouer your Britaine Soueraigne and his Royall off-ſpring you were protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, deliuered.)</p>
               <p>Doe you thinke, that the Holy Father, was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, with that moſt helliſh attempt of thoſe ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie locuſts? Could GARNET, GERRARD, TES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOND, with their Ignatianed Diſciples be actours, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals? Could STANLEY, OWEN, know it? Could Antwerpe, and the Low-countrie mutter of ſome great Alteration, not of the heauens, but of Englands Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Could PARSONS, CRESWELL, bee not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt? And could it be concealed from AQVAVIVA, the Generall of the holy quarell; or he hide it from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, <hi>Paule</hi> the fifth? Who will once imagine this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:17743:29"/> that hath beene but once acquainted with the Ignatians manner of proceedings? And what doth the holy Father now reſt? hath the late moſt happy and miraculous deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of all Englands glorie, daunted his courage ſo; that hee will proiect no more villanie of like kind? God grant it be ſo: but, it is to be doubted, he will not ſurceaſe, vntill hee be conſumed by the ſpirit of Gods mouth, as moſt infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he will one day.</p>
               <p>Idle are the prophecies which flie vp and downe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially amongſt the ſpeudo-Ieſuited and Ignatianed Papiſts: I will relate none of them becauſe I contemne them as ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, vnworthy of the eares of ſo honourable an audience: yet giue mee leaue to mention a bloudie peece of one of them; and a little to demurre vpon the ſame. <hi>A Pope for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth ſhall fight againſt two Engliſh Kings, and with bloudie handes ſhall bleſſe England.</hi> The moſt gratious God, as he hath confounded them often, and <hi>who broke their necks the fifth of Nouember,</hi> doth doubtleſſe ſuffer them to bee delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their vaine prophecies, and will, I moſt humbly truſt and pray, ſubuert all their wicked enterpriſes. But ſeeing prophecies are myſticall, and myſtically to be interpreted, eſpecially ſuch as are paper ones, deſcribed by pictures, as they ſay, this is: I will deliuer my conceit what I thinke, may be vnderſtood, by theſe bloudie handes of the Pope; For my part I cannot better interpret the ſame, then thus: That by the Popes bloudie handes, the Ignatians are to be vnderſtood, and by the bloudie fingers their Ignatianed, and diſloyall foranized Diſciples, be they Prieſts or Laikes, (I alwaies except temperate and moderate Recuſants, of which, I know, ſome of the Laitie, to be very true hearted and loyall Engliſh, as likewiſe I cannot doubt, but that there are ſome moderate Secular Prieſts, I meane ſuch, as are vn-Ignatianed.) For, were not ſuch, and only ſuch Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and Ignatianed, the Powder-Miners, and Powder-Locuſts? Are not ſuch only, or moſt ſingularly thoſe, who euery where, at home, and abrode, in forraigne Countries,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17743:29"/> doe ſeeke to diſgrace the Magiſtrates (Soueraigne not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) of theſe Kingdomes, and if any of them haue any vice or defect (and who liueth without ſome one at leaſt?) they will aggrauate the ſame; yea, and rather then faile, they will deuiſe new, vaine, and thoſe moſt foule and filthy, in the forge of their owne wicked braines (oh how meete is it that ſuch as are eminent ſhould be careful of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſations when they are beſieged with ſuch malitious Zoiles?) Such only, or chiefly, are they, who will gladly talke or preſage of the decay of our ſhipping; delightfully reaſon of the conſuming of our Kings treaſure, pleaſingly commune of the decay, and fall of martiall men; ioyfully liſten after mutterings, or any leaſt diſcontents, in the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous multitudes; againſt gouernment or Gouernours: theſe are they, who gladly diſcourſe of forraigne powers, forraine preparations: theſe are they who vnwillingly and fearefully hear of the admirable proweſſe and martiall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie of our moſt hopefull <hi>Alexander,</hi> or rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and moſt deare Prince <hi>Henrie:</hi> theſe are they (to be ſhort) who delight in nothing more, take con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and hope in nothing more, than to heare of fallings out and quarrels betwixt thoſe of the Scottiſh and Engliſh Nation; hoping, deſiring, and expecting, that from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall quarrells they may come to bee Nationall. Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, right Worſhipfull, and moſt worthie Chriſtians, all that are here preſent, from the higheſt to the loweſt; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you all, in reſpect of your dutie to Chriſt Crucified, in reſpect of your dutie to your Soueraigne, loue to your Countrie, care of your owne ſafeties, and the flouriſhing ſtate of Chriſts Church and Ghoſpel, haue no ſuch quarrels amongſt you; and if any ſuch ariſe, appeaſe them ſpeedily, end them Chriſtianly: Beleeue it, beleeue it, nothing will pleaſe the Ignatianed Papiſts more (I except ſtill the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate) nothing can be more gratefull to their holy Father, then to vnderſtand that the Subiects of two ſo honourable nations, vnder ſo peaceable, ſo gratious, and ſo religious a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17743:30"/> Soueraigne ſhould haue any iarres and contentions. How often, Catholike hearers, haue I heard <hi>Robert Parſons, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Creſwell,</hi> preſagingly hope for ſuch contentions vpon vnion of the two kingdomes, whereby, as hee and they all thinke (and wiſely thinke, if it ſhould ſo fall out: but God auert it) the vnconquerable and inuincible power of this kingdome (vnder God, and by God protected) might be broken and weakened: and alas who is ſo ſimple a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecturer as can not preſage vpon whoſe head the beane would be bruiſed and broken: doubtleſſe the beginner of any ſuch quarrell by all Britaines ſhould deſerue to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted as a moſt deteſtable Anatheme, worthy all execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But to returne to the bloudie hands of the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Rome: conſanguineous, and of the ſame blood with theſe, were thoſe Ignatian <hi>Valladolidian Padres,</hi> of the Engliſh Seminarie: who, when the proclamation for our moſt gratious Soueraigne was brought vnto them, by a Spaniſh Duke, were ſo ſtrangely daunted therewith; thus it was. Thoſe Engliſh Padres, had long time held that king of Spaine, and the Nobles of that kingdome, in expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of great matters, to be done, at the death of Queene <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> of happy memory, for the bringing of the <hi>Infanta</hi> of Spaine into this kingdome, vpon the fantaſticall Title to this Crowne: but that Heroiſſe being departed, and our moſt gratious Soueraigne being almoſt euen with the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vp of her ghoſt, moſt ioyfully in this city proclaimed: Copies of the ſaid Proclamation were with al ſpeed by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers, ſent into ſome forraine Countries, and into Spaine alſo, where, preſently vpon the freſh receit of one of them, a certaine great Spaniſh Duke, poſteth in his Caroch with all ſpeed, to the Engliſh Fathers of the Seminarie in Valladolid, who firſt demandeth of them what newes out of England? or what expectations they had, of any good to be done there? According to their accuſtomed anſwers their vnnaturall and vnengliſhed ſpirites they forſooth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and hoped for much at the death of Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17743:30"/> for their Spaniſh Lady: till then (as they ſaide) their hopes were but weake, but ſmall, but cold. Well anſwered the Duke, If you heare no news, here then is news for you, and withall he preſented to them a printed Proclamation for the moſt ioyfull acknowledgement of our Soueraigne king <hi>Iames:</hi> where now (ſaith the duke) be your great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? where now are your expectations? where now are your hopes at the death of <hi>Q Elizabeth?</hi> They ſtood as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſtoniſhed, danted, and confounded, that they had ſcarſe a word to ſay. The Duke obſeruing their confuſion preſently departeth, diſcourſeth with ſom perſons of note, who were with him in his Caroch, touching the buſie ſpirites of thoſe engliſh Padres, greatly laughing at their follies, their vaine promiſes and expectations. But theſe holy Fathers, not able to contain their griefe, giue notice of the vnexpected news to ſome of their fauorites, among their ſcholers, wherof one of them, preſently as one ready to burſt, coms in haſt, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth his ſtomacke to his fellows thus: We are vndone my maſters, we are vndone, (God graunt it, and let all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſay Amen,) <hi>Iames</hi> of Scotland is proclaimed King of England. Theſe things being true, &amp; iuſtly imputed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with much more that I haue obſerued in my Motiues, may I be thought vnfitly to haue interpreted, the Popes bloudy hands, &amp; fingers, wherewith he inceſſantly labours to bleſſe England, to be theſe Ignatian Fathers, &amp; their Ignatianed children? O England, or rather, O Britany! reuiued in thy Britaine Soueraigne: Thinke on theſe bloody hands &amp; fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and be euer vigilant: Remember thy late miraculous deliuerie, and be euer thankefull to thy Almightie and All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull Deliuerer: Remember thy late danger, &amp; be euer watchfull: Remember how as God then deliuered thee, ſo he alſo vouchſafed to inſpire thee, that thy Soueraigne with thee did then prouide an Oath, as a Touchſtone, whereby the diſloyall and forranized Spirites might bee diſcerned from the Naturall and Temperate: Doeſt thou make vſe of Gods Doctrine? Doſt thou apply this touchſtone? and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17743:31"/> diſtinguiſh, vpon what ſpirit it is refuſed, either out of a Womaniſh ſcrupuloſitie (for ſome few feminine men in ſwearing are perhaps like to ſcrupulous women) or out of inueterated diſloyaltie, and grounded hereſie? if ſo, it is well and moſt happy for Englands ſecuritie; for Englands Poſteritie, our Children, our Childrens Children will bleſſe ſuch prouidence, &amp;c. But I obſerue the time is very farre ſpent, that I cannot proſecute my diuiſion of my Text ſo fully as I deſired: therefore I muſt be briefe; it followeth in my Text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Who by the Eternall Spirit offered himſelfe vnſpotted to God.</head>
               <p>In theſe wordes the Apoſtle deliuereth vnto the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, what the Sacrifice is, which he ſo highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto them; how it is offered; to whom it is offered; by whom, or through whom it is offered. The ſacrifice of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered is Chriſt, who alſo is the high Prieſt, offering and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing himſelfe moſt voluntarily, freely, and vnſpotted, to his Father: The Perſon, to whom the ſacrifice is offered deſigned by that word <hi>(Deo) to God.</hi> But what is that, by which, or through which this Sacrifice is offered. Heare the Apoſtle (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>By, or through the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſpirit,</hi> as if he ſhould haue ſpecially expreſſed it thus: by the Eternall God-head, by the eternall euerlaſting Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie. Here, here, Chriſtian Hearers, are miſteries of loue, of faith, of admiration, of exceſſe, of diuine wiſedome, of exceſſe and an infinite exceſſe of diuine goodneſſe, of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power, of which exceſſe <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> communed with Chriſt vpon the Mount <hi>Thabor,</hi> ſo ſaith the Scripture <hi>(Loquebantur de exceſſu eius) they ſpake of his exceſſe.</hi> What an exceſſe, aboue all humane intelligence, wher God and the Diuinitie is concurring in euery circumſtance of this Sacrifice? God the Prieſt, God the Sacrifice, God the receiuer of the Sacrifice; and God the Dignifier, the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier, and Beautifier of the ſacrifice, and yet all theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are in one God. Theſe conſiderations doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17743:31"/> me, and produce a ſtrange admiration in my ſoule, that the moſt infinite Trinitie ſhould ſo buſie themſelues, himſelfe to make and accompliſh a bloudie ſacrifice, of one of that infinite ſocietie: but in no reſpect, I am touched with greater admiration, then to conſider how moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, moſt voluntarily, the infinite maieſtie of Chriſt, did conſent to dedicate himſelfe to the ignominious death of the Croſſe; did conſent to offer himſelfe, to giue himſelfe as a free gift, for the deliuerance of moſt vngratefull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde. <hi>(Dedit ſemetipſum, &amp;c.) He gaue himſelfe</hi> (<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit</hi> 2.</note> ſaith the holy Apoſtle to <hi>Titus) that the might redeeme vs:</hi> That which is giuen, you know Catholike hearets, is put out of the power and poſſeſſion of the giuer, and is at the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him, to whom the gift is made; and you know, that the ſtrongeſt, the abſoluteſt manner of paſſing away any goods is by deed of gift, as being irreuocable, O ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble myſterie! Chriſt giueth himſelfe, makes an irreuocable deede of gift of his bloud to his Father? yea, but not only to him; to ſuch faithfull beleeuers that ſhould confide in him? yea, but not only to them? to whom farther? to who elſe? marry, he putteth himſelfe into the power, dominion, and diſpoſing of thoſe damned and reprobate miſcreants the Iewes; that they ſhould vorke their pleaſure on him, <note place="margin">Iſai. 50.</note>
                  <hi>(genas dedit vellentibus, corpus perentientibus,) His cheekes he gaue to be pulled, rented, his bodie,</hi> his whole bodie, <hi>to bee ſmitten,</hi> and this that wee who were in the ſlauerie of ſinne, and Satan, might be made free, by ſo great a grace; and be put in the free poſſeſſion &amp; diſpoſing of our ſelues, within that moſt diuine Paradiſe, which his moſt ſacred bloud ſhould eternally water and ſanctifie. What a humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation? what an offering is this? The holy Apoſtle admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereat, pronounceth thus: (<hi>Humiliauit ſemetipſum &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath humbled himſelfe, made obedient vnto death, euen to the death of the Croſſe;</hi>) that he might exalt and honour vs. What a myſterie of loue? that hee might raiſe vs vp to life, he debaſeth himſelfe to death. For this purpoſe being
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17743:32"/> in the forme of God he putteth on him the ſhape of man; that is much: but heare more. The forme of a Man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the law, ſubiect to the law; yet more, he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the condition and qualitie of a ſinfull man: yet more, hee is arraied and clothed with the iniquities of all mankinde: yet more, hee is made vpon the Croſſe as a curſe, as a malediction for mankinde: yet more, or moſt of all, vpon that Croſſe, before the Tribunall of his Eternall Father, bee ſuſtaineth the Perſon of all mankinde, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goeth his diſpleaſure (ſuch <hi>a diſpleaſure in which is life, Pſalme</hi> 30.) he hath that iudgment pronounced vpon him and againſt him, which mankinde had deſerued; ſo heauily, ſo grieuouſly, that in the infliction of the iudgement, and the execution of the ſentence; as Man <hi>he cried out my God my God, why haſt thou forſaken me:</hi> and yet as man he could not bee ſwallowed vp, <hi>nor held long with the torments and terrours of death.</hi> What a progreſſe is here? what a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie of greateſt humiliation, for the Sonne of God, thus to offer himſelfe to his Father as a malediction, that in him wee all might bee a benediction, and a bleſſing in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly holies of holies? what an abiſſe of humiliation, that he offereth himſelfe alone; no man of the Nations, no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Iewes, no Angel from the heauens helping him, aſſiſting him, <hi>(Torcular caleat ſolus) but himſelfe alone, hee alone treadeth the Preſſe</hi> of his moſt bitter Paſſion: there was indeed a Trinitie of deuout Perſons; the two <hi>Maries,</hi> and the Diſciple whom Ieſus loued, ſtanding, or languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with griefe by the Croſſe; by that their preſence and attendance, they gaue teſtimonie of their loues, and moſt ſincere compaſſion; but nothing able to releeue him, to comfort him, who had hoiſed himſelfe vp, vpon the Altar of the Croſſe, out of their reaches towards the heauens, and to the view of his heauenly Father, in heauen; where the price of our Redemption, of our Reconciliation, was to be made and paied. What a ſmelling, and a moſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmelling ſauour, did reeke vp from that preſſe, and Altar
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17743:32"/> of the Croſſe, to the Noſtrills of the eternall Iudge, and moſt iuſt God? by him moſt worthily, moſt deſiredly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and receiued: receiuing <hi>(duplicia de manu Domini,) a twofold, a double price from the hand of the Lord,</hi> our dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Eſai 40.</note> Lord. Surely, if no other dignitie had beene in this our Lords perſon, who offered himſelfe: yet the ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble chatitie, the vnſpeakable loue, wherewith he ſo freely dedicated himſelfe to death, to ſatisfie his Fathers heauie diſpleaſure, would haue made the ſacrifice to be moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily eſteemed.</p>
               <p>But there is a Dignitie, there is an Excellencie in this high Prieſts ſacrificing himſelfe, which did make the ſame ſacrifice, not only by acceptance and fauour, but euen out of the worth and ineſtimable valew of it, to bee accepted and admitted, as a compleat, conſummate ſatisfaction, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, in very perfection of iuſtice and ſatisfaction, of all, and for all, who ſhould ſtedfaſtly beleeue, and confide in it. What dignitie is this? what worthineſſe is this? you will aske and demand of me: Our Apoſtle ſhall anſwere; heare him (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Who by the eternall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit offered himſelfe.</hi> This eternall Spirit, the Diuinitie of the ſecond perſon in Trinitie, by reaſon of the hypoſtaticall and perſonall vnion of it with the humanitie, communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto the ſame humanitie an infinite dignitie; the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dignitie and vnſpeakable excellencie, of the God-head it ſelfe; and by reaſon of the ſame perſonall Vnion, the operations and actions of this perſon, (for <hi>operationes ſunt ſuppoſitorum, Operations and actions are of the perſons and ſuppoſites themſelues</hi>) though immediately, proceeding from the humanitie, or the ſoule of Chriſt, or any power of his ſoule, or bodie: doe receiue and are dignified, with an infinite kinde of valour, dignitie, and eſtimation; as being the operations of God and Man: and although there be no Phiſicall, Diuines or Supernaturall impreſſion, or qualitie, giuen to theſe actions, yet the only procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of theſe operations from ſuch a perſon, hauing ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17743:33"/> an excellencie, and dignitie, intrinſecally with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelfe, giueth vnto them an extrinſecall valour, by which they are eſteemed, and regarded, as the very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of God himſelfe, by which hee offereth and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe to his Father: and therefore, no tongue, neither of Man nor Angell, can deliuer how infinitely deſeruing they are, of eſteeme, and regard: the only knowledge of God, which is infinite, can comprehend their worth and valour.</p>
               <p>If I ſhould ſtand largely to proue this, you would thinke that I held theſe my Auditors, to bee but of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intelligence. Few of you are ſo ignorant, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but conceiue, that according to the dignitie or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Perſon, is the morall worth, and eſteeme of the action, which proceedeth from ſuch a Perſon: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect worthy, is a ſalutation or honourable vſe, which commeth from a worthy Gentleman; more worthy, that which commeth from a Knight; worthier is the ſame from a Baron; aboue that, is the ſame, proceeding from an Earle, a Duke: but of higheſt eſteeme, is that, which is giuen from a Prince, and if there were any earthly Prince, of infinite worth, and excellencie, in the intrinſecall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of his perſon, the actions and operations of ſuch a Prince, in morall eſtimation, would haue a morall kinde of infinitie. Here-hence it is, that our high Prieſt Ieſus, whoſe dignitie was the very God-head it ſelfe, whoſe Perſon was of infinite Maieſtie, did immediately, and by it ſelfe, communicate vnto his operations and actions, an infinite kinde of morall worthineſſe and valour; by which they were ſo eleuated, that being preſented to the ſight of the diuine Maieſtie; in very rigour of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and perfection of Satisfaction, and Merit, they were equiualent, ſuper-excellent, and ſurpaſſing all the malice of ſinne, which mankinde had, or could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit: and therefore, this our high Prieſt offering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by the eternall Spirit, (thus dignifying, and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17743:33"/> his actions and operations:) to his Heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the Redemption of Mankinde; did by the ſame Oblation and Sacrifice, ſo fully, ſo abundantly, ſo perfectly, ſo iuſtly, ſo deſeruingly, purchaſe vs to himſelfe, and reconcile vs to his Father; that his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could not refuſe his face, making interceſſions and ſupplications for vs, vpon the Altar of the Croſſe: and this is that, which our Apoſtle pronounceth in this his ſame Epiſtle to the Hebrewes: of the infinite worthineſſe and excellencie of Chriſt? <note place="margin">Hebr. 5</note>
                  <hi>Qui in diebus carnis ſuae, &amp;c.) Who in the daies of his fleſh, with teares, and a loude crie, offering vp praiers and ſupplications to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who was able to ſaue him from death, was heard for his Reuerence:</hi> So great, (Catholike and Chriſtian Hearers) ſo infinite was the reuerence and excellencie of CHRIST, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was the Sonne of GOD; that his Father could not, but heare his requeſts and ſupplications, made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for vs: and from this reuerence, and from this worthineſſe hath his fleſh valour, efficacie, and force, to cleanſe our conſciences from dead workes, to ſerue the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</p>
               <p>Heare to this purpoſe, (but what neede I authoritie of any man to confirme ſo manifeſt a truth:) Saint AVSTEN, <note place="margin">Aug. lib. 10. de Ciuit. cap. 24.</note>(<hi>Non ergo Caro Chriſti, per ſe ipſum mundat credentes, ſed perverbum à quo ſuſcepta eſt: Therefore the fleſh of Christ doth not by it ſelfe cleanſe the beleeuers, but by the word, of which it was taken and aſſumpted:</hi> and this is that which AQVINAS hath moſt clearely. <note place="margin">Aquin q. 48. art. 6. in cap. &amp; ad 1. &amp; ad 2. eodem art.</note>
                  <hi>(Efficiens principale humanae ſalutis, eſt Deus: Quia vero humanitas Christi, eſt diuinitatis inſtrumentum, ideo ea conſequenti, omnes actiones &amp; paſsiones Chriſti, inſtrumentaliter operantur in virtute diuinitatis, ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem humanam; &amp; ſecundum hoc, Paſsio Chriſti, effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienter cauſat ſalutem humanam. The principall effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, of ſaluation of mankinde is God; but becauſe the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie of Chriſt, is the inſtrument of his diuinitie; therefore
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17743:34"/> conſequently, all the operations and actions of Chriſt, do worke in the vertue of the diuinitie, to the ſaluation of mankinde.</hi> And in his anſwere to the firſt obiection, thus moſt clearely (<hi>Paſio Chriſti &amp;c.) the paſsion of Chriſt, referred to the fleſh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>of Chriſt, anſwereth and is agreeing to the infirmitie aſſumpted;</hi> but <hi>referred to his diuinitie, hath thereby, an infinite vertue or efficacie:</hi> Thus he; which I partly bring, to confirme what I haue ſaid, partly to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificians, who gladly would calumniate the Church of England, for her doctrine touching the concurrence of Chriſts diuinitie in the office, and acts of his moſt high Prieſt-hood.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I here plunge my ſelfe into that depth, in to that profound abiſſe of diſcourſing, of the manner of Chriſts concurring as a Prieſt, by reaſon of his diuinitie and humanitie, for the ſaluation of mankind? no, no: (<hi>Sermo in-interpretabilis) the ſpeech would bee uninterpretabile:</hi> my ſhallow conceite, would bee ouerplunged in ſuch a depth: it is enough for vs, at this preſent, to vnderſtand, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that by reaſon of the perſonall vnitie, not only the humane nature, but very Chriſt God himſelfe, was offered to his Father, and offered himſelfe to his Father, and alſo, this diuine nature, had his concurrence in the ſuffering, of his humanitie, that the ſame conſented to his ſuffering, and did in a wonderfull ſort particularly gouerne, comfort and ſtrengthen the ſaid humanitie, as being a principall and proper part of himſelfe; that it might ſuffer, and be offered in ſuch obedience to the Father, to the death of the moſt ignominious croſſe. I ſhall not here need, to inſiſt vpon the third branch, of my diuiſion: by the which our Apoſtle diſtinguiſheth, to whom this ſacrifice is offered; to wit to God: For, if all ſacrifices are to be conſecrated as ſacred vnto him; to whome elſe ſhould the ſacrifice of a God, and from a God bee offered then to God himſelfe? neither ſhall I neede to dwell any whit in this diſcourſe, to ſhew how this Chriſt, this ſacrifice, was vnſpotted; without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17743:34"/> and moſt immaculate: I could not eſteeme it leſſe then blaſphemie in me, to ſeeme to diſcourſe thereupon, and by way of argument to proue it: for can it ſinke into the imagination of any, that God ſhould bee, or could bee ſpotted with any ſinne, imperfection or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh thereof? Our Chriſt indeed, tooke vpon him the ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of a ſinner, but it was impoſſible to the abſolute and almightie power of God, to haue permitted him, to haue beene taynted with any the leaſt internall or true blemiſh of ſinne. Yea by the omnipotent power of God, would not hinder or let it, but that by vertue of the perſſinall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hypoſtolicall coniunction, the ſoule of Chriſt was ſo ſanctified, and repleniſhed, with all graces, that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and moſt neceſſarily it was impeceable, vnſinneable, and not capable of any the leſt ſpot of ſinne. And it was indeed moſt meet that our high Prieſt ſhould be ſuch a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>impolluted, innocent, ſeparated from ſinnes, and made higher then the very heauens</hi> themſelues, as being the Lord and God of themand all that is in them. And ſo, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, to the laſt branch of my diuiſion in which is thus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Shall cleanſe the conſcience, from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God.</head>
               <p>Here is the ſcope of Chriſts bloud offered; here is the end of Chriſts offering himſelfe, by the Eternall Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to God: that our conſciences might be cleanſed from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God. Good God, what are men, or the conſciences of men that thou doeſt ſo viſit them? thou doeſt ſo eſteeme them? what are they that, to cleanſe them, thou diddeſt ſo farre depreſſe and humble thy only begotten Sonne, vnder thy Angels, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to an ignominious death, to make man equall with Angells in euerlaſting life? it is thy vnſpeakeable loue and charitie: no deſeruing of ours at all. But how? by what meanes? by what inſtrument, is this cleanſing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice applied to our conſciences, to cleanſe them from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17743:35"/> dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God. God made heauen &amp; earth and all in them, made man and all belonging to him without any concurrence or helpe from him by that word (<hi>fiat, fiat</hi>) be it done bee it made. Doth he ſo cleanſe the conſcience of man, from dead works, without any act of man, as a meanes, as an inſtrument, to applie this ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſacrifice to his conſcience? no, no: Heare the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.) <hi>Being iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fied gratis frankly, by the grace of him, by the redemption which is in Chriſt Ieſus whom God hath propoſed, a propitiation by faith in his bloud:</hi> by faith therefore, by a liuing faith, Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s propoſed a propitiation in his bloud (not in mans works) to euery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing conſcience. Indefinite, vniuerſall, is this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this propitiation, by faith in his bloud, to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, all ſexes, all conditions, in all times and in all ages: no perſon whatſoeuer, is excluded from faith &amp; confidence in it, no not Iudas himſelfe, who betrayed it, had he beene ſo happie; not the crucifying Iewes, had they beene ſo fortunate.</p>
               <p>How powerfull a ſound faith in this bloud, is to cleanſe conſciences; let <hi>Leo</hi> an Ancient Pope confront againſt theſe latter Pontificians all of them being meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts (<hi>de condigno</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>de congruo) out of condignitie</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruitie</hi> to their firſt or ſecond iuſtification (for ſuch a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, their nouell Scholaſticall hereſie hath denied.) <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ſept. m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſ.</note>
                  <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio pro iniuſtis iuſti ſanguinis, tam potens fuit ad praemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, tam diues ad praetium, vt ſivniuerſitas Captiuorum, in Redemptorem ſuum crederent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alium, tyrannica vincula re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinerent. The effuſion</hi> (ſaith this Pope) <hi>of the iuſt bloud, for the vniuſt was ſo potent for a reward, ſo rich for a price, that if the whole vniuerſitie of Captiues would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in their Redeemer, the bands of the Tyrant ſhould hold or retaine none.</hi> To him I adioyne Saint <hi>Auſten: Modo fratres, vt a peccato ſanemur, Chriſtum crucifixum intu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17743:35"/> quomodo illi intuebantur illum ſerpentem, &amp; a morſibus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. tract. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Ioh.</note> 
                  <hi>ſanabantur ſerpentium; ſic qui fide intuentur mortem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, ſanantur morſibus peccatornm ſed illi ſanabantur a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, a d vitam temporalem; hi autem, vt habeant vitam aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam; hoc enim intereſt inter figuratam imaginem, &amp; rem ipſam: figura praeſtabat vitam temporalem, res ipſa cuius ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go erat, praeſtabat vitam aeternam. Now brethren<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that we may be healed from ſinne, let vs behold Chriſt cruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, euen as they beheld that Serpent,</hi> (hee ſpeaketh of the Iewes in the Deſart) <hi>and were healed of the biting of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents; ſo they who in faith behold the death of Chriſt, are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the biting of ſinne: but they were healed from death, to a temporall life; but theſe, that they may haue life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: for this is the difference, betwixt the figuring image, and the thing it ſelfe: the figure gaue temporall life, but the thing it ſelfe of which the Image was gaue euerlaſting life.</hi> Thus hee with infinite much like, which might bee produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of him, and all Ancient Fathers, agreeingly to the whole current of ſacred Scriptures, for iuſtification by faith; againſt the doctrine of all Pontificians who require a poſitiue, and immediate concurrence (diſpoſitiue and, preparatiue at leſt) of mans workes, to the firſt iuſtification, too to derogatorie againſt the bloud of Chriſt and faith in it.</p>
               <p>How pernicious is that poſition of many of them, that the works which doe proceede, and goe before iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doe, (<hi>de congruo</hi>) out of congruitie, merit iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? ſhal I cal this, tenent, an incongruous poſition only? not ſo: it is hereticall; it is damnable, not onely in the teachers, but in the conſenters and approuers of the ſame: For tell mee, All yee Pontifician Meritiſts <hi>out of congruitie and de congrua,</hi> as you ſpeake: can the power of God? can the iuſtice of God? can the wiſedome of God? doe any thing? diſpoſe any thing? or proceede in any thing? againſt congruitie, right, equitie decencie? No ſurely, you muſt anſwere; vnles like madmen you wil affirme
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17743:36"/> that his wiſedome may doe ſome thing vncongruouſly, his power may worke ſomething indecently, inconueniently, vnſeemely: you are not yet ſo impudent, as to denie the attributes of God his infinite Wiſedome, Iuſtice, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and conſequently his God-head: ſee then and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue what your <hi>merit of congruitie</hi> produceth: marry, a <hi>merit of condignitie;</hi> for ſuch a conueniencie, ſuch a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruitie,</hi> ſuch a worthineſſe of a worke to God, is as a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie.</hi> For I demand of you in good earneſt. Is not that a merit of condignitie, which in reſpect of the diſpoſition of the worker, and worthineſſe of the worke, ſo bindeth, vrgeth, and conſtraineth the omnipotent hand of God, that he cannot (vnleſſe hee will proceede againſt decencie and congruitie) but reſpect, regard, and reward the ſame with ſubſequent and following iuſtification in the ſoule which hath it? whereby then, it is as cleare as the Sunne, that from merits of congruitie preceding iuſtification, you are come to merits of condignitie, preceding the ſame: by which your hereticall condignitie, you are condignely fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from Chriſt, you are condignely fallen from the iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation which is in Chriſt; which is only by <hi>grace, not by</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>workes;</hi> otherwiſe, <hi>grace ſhould not be grace,</hi> if the Apoſtles argument, in his Epiſtle to the Romanes may ſtand, and take place: and that of the ſame Apoſtle alſo to <hi>Titus</hi> ſtand firme. (<hi>Nos iuſtificatos eſſe, illius gratia, vt haeredes efficeremur aeternavitae.) That we are iuſtified by his grace, that we might bee made Heires of euerlaſting life.</hi> And that againe of the ſame Apoſtle, in his Epiſtle to the Romanes. (<hi>Iuſtificati ergo ex fide, &amp;c.) We being iuſtified therefore by</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>faith, let vs haue peace to God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord; by whom we haue acceſſe by faith, into this grace, in which we ſtand, and doe glorie, in the hope of the glorie, of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How admirable therefore is the excellencie of Chriſtian faith, by which the faithfull beleeuer is iuſtified in Chriſt, is inſerted to Chriſt? made the Sonne of God? the Heire of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17743:36"/> heauen? partaker of iuſtice? poſſeſſor of life? not by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing merits of his owne, but by the ſame faith, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all the merits and iuſtice of Chriſt, which thereby are efficaciouſly for his iuſtification, communicated vnto him. But what? doe wee by this extolling of faith, and by this comfortable doctrine of iuſtification by faith, ſubuert the neceſſitie of good workes? God forbid: doe we grant a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, or impunitie of ſinning? God auert it: doe wee grant a Chriſtian ſecuritie, and hope of ſaluation without merits? Yes, without merits; but not without good works, not without the fruits of ſanctification, which God hath ordained prepared and commanded his elect to walke in. Heare that learned man maſter <hi>Caluin</hi> cap. 10. of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned inſtitutions (that his propugnacle and defence of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion which no Pontifician durſt euer yet attempt to confute) Per fidei iuſtificationem &amp;c. <hi>By iuſtification by faith the Aduerſaries cauill good works to bee deſtroied, what if thereby, they be more eſtabliſhed? for we dreame not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of a faith voide of good works, or of a iuſtification, which conſiſteth without them; this is only the difference, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we confeſſe faith, and good works neceſſarily to cohere toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; notwithſtanding, we place iuſtification in faith, and not in works: And the ſame, by what meanes it is done, it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to explicate, if wee conuert our ſelues to Christ, to whom our faith is directed, and from whome, it receiueth all vertue and force; why therefore are we iuſtified by it? becauſe by faith we apprehend the iuſtice of Chriſt, by which only, we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God: But this thou maiſt not apprehend, vnleſſe thou doe withall apprehend his ſanctification; for he is giuen to vs, for Iuſtice, VViſedome, Redemption, Sanctification, therefore Chriſt iuſtifieth no man, whom hee doth not alſo ſanctifie: For theſe benefits, are with an inſolluble knot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned; ſo that whom Chriſt illuminateth, thoſe hee redeemeth; whome he redeemeth, hee iuſtifieth; whome bee iuſtifieth, hee ſanctifieth:</hi> thus hee moſt excellently; agreeingly to ſacred ſcriptures and all antiquitie; conformably to the faith of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17743:37"/> the Church of England; and accordingly to the Chriſtian doctrine, and reſolution of all reformed Churches, as the harmonie of confeſſions teſtifieth. And I dare auouch, that the vniuerſall and Catholike concordance, of this funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall point of iuſtification, (without which no Church and no perſon can bee held for Chriſtian (in the ſtrict, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and true acception of the name of Chriſtian) is more v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformely taught and held, by all the reformed Churches, then any point of Doctrine controuerted in theſe times, is held by the Pontiſicans: How glad would they be, had they but ſuch a vnity and conformitie for the verie rule of their faith touching which they are not yet agreed as I haue ſhewed in my motiues. But the conformitie and irrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible agreement of all reformed Churches, for this fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall article of iuſtification, by faith in the bloud of Chriſt Ieſus, as it is an euidentargument of Chriſts ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and tendeth greatly to the glorie of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; ſo it produceth wonderfull and vnmoueable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in the ſoules of the faithfull and ſanctified belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. The aduerſarie, forſooth, frame vnto themſelues an Hiſtoricall beleefe for iuſtification in Chriſt; the which <hi>as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the Diuels haue,</hi> and yet notwithſtanding doe <hi>tremble:</hi> ſo the Chriſtian auncient Churches neuer knew it, and the Reformed doe explode it: and againſt iuſtification by this Hiſtoricall faith, they muſter argument vpon argumentt; and produce text vpon text; to ſhew, that beſides ſuch a faith, there is required neceſſitie of good works, and the fruits of ſanctification. But alas, (<hi>oleum &amp; operam perdunt) they waſt their oyle and looſe their labour.</hi> For what Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reformed Church euer taught ſuch a blaſphemous para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe, of iuſtification by ſuch an Hiſtoricall faith? they vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deteſt, abhominate and renounce ſuch a iuſtifying faith. And here, giue me leaue, moſt beloued and Catholike Auditours, to feele the very pulſes of your conſciences, and my owne alſo; to ſee how you ſtand, and whether wee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17743:37"/> are cleanſed with the bloud of Chriſt, or no, by this iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, by this ſanctifying faith. Doe you at any time, perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the purpoſe of ſinne, deſire of ſinne, perſwade your ſelues, that notwithſtanding the ſame, you are iuſtified in Chriſt, apprehending him by a dead faith as your Sauiour? Doe you at any time, hauing a conſcience to act ſinne, to commit, approue, conſent to ſinne; thinke that Chriſt not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding will iuſtifie and ſanctifie you, without hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acknowledgement and heartie deteſtation of the ſaid ſinnes? if the Diuell (hauing transformed himſelfe) haue lulled any of you into ſuch a lethargie, I muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, that ſuch a confidence, is but a mere preſumption, ſuch a iuſtification is a moſt pernicious deprauation. But ariſe, ariſe, and Chriſt will illuminate you, and will tell you<note place="margin">1. Joh. 1</note> what you ought to doe. (<hi>Si confiteamur peccata &amp;c.) If</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iacob 2.</note> 
                  <hi>we confeſſe and acknowledge our ſinnes, God is faithfull to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Joh. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>them. Againe he who ſaith, he knoweth God, (by a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith) and keepeth not his commandements is a lyar, and the truth is not in him.</hi> Againe (<hi>Omnis quinatus eſt ex Deo non peccat &amp;c.) Euery one, who is borne of God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not, becauſe the ſeed of God, remaineth in him; neither can he ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God.</hi> Millions of like paſſages of ſacred Scripture, might be produced to ſhew that no man can be iuſtified in Chriſt, whiles with full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and with a ſetled intention and purpoſe of ſinne, hee proſecuteth the ſame: doubtleſſe it were a moſt pernicious paradoxe, to teach, that Chriſt iuſtifieth any one, while hee is propoſing and proſecuting with full and free conſent<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> ſinne, the <hi>hire and wages whereof are death and damnation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. 3.</note> If any one here, ſhould bee ſo dangerouſly ſeduced by the <hi>fallacie of ſinne,</hi> and deceit of Sathan, let him awake from ſo prophane a perſwaſion; or elſe, I muſt needes tell him, that as much as in him lieth, hee <hi>doth conculcate the bloud of the New Teſtament, and doth eſteeme the bloud of Chriſt as polluted:</hi> for, were it not a pollution
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17743:38"/> euen in the bloud of Chriſt it ſelfe, ſo to partake, ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to communicate with ſinne? to iuſtifie a conſcience actually, deliberately polluting, and contaminating it ſelfe with ſinne? be it ſpoken with reuerence, it is a thing which the infinite goodnes of God cannot doe, cannot effectuate. How lamentable therefore is the ſtate of certaine ſinners, who alwaies liue in the ſtate of ſinne, and infallible occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinne? who therefore cannot (vnleſſe they bee moſt preſumptuouſly made) euer eſteeme themſelues to be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied through faith in Chriſt; and ſo conſequently, neuer feele the true comfort of the ſoule which ariſeth from a Chriſtian perſwaſion of iuſtification in Chriſt: I meane not ſuch perſons, who through infirmitie and ignorance may fall <hi>ſeuen (yea ſeuentie ſeuen) times in a day, and riſe againe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou 24</note> but I meane ſuch, as ſtill are falling and neuer ariſe; becauſe they are faſt bound, and chained in the occaſion and ſtate of ſinne: I meane ſuch auaricious perſons, be they Church men or Laikes, which doe deteſt Papiſticall idolatrie; and yet themſelues daily, and inceſſantly doe commit their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall idolatrie, and whordome with their gold and ſiluer; with their continuall beholding, ſolicitous and couetous turning, winding, telling, locking, and vnlocking, medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, caring, contemplating, adoring, worſhipping of their Idolls: and yet preſumptuous fooles, moſt ignorant Doctors of the law, they will thinke themſelues to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in Chriſt, becauſe they can talke of iuſtification in Chriſt, without workes: alas, alas, they ſhould rather tremble with the Deuills, and with remorſe of conſcience, bewaile their damnable ſtate in which they liue, and bee moſt aſſured, that whilſt they ſerue ſuch Mammons in their cheſts, they cannot ſerue Chriſt in their ſoules, nor be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in Chriſt in their hearts. I meane ſuch wanton ones, who abuſe and ſeparate themſelues from their nuptiall bed and doe glew their ſoules to their Concubines, whome they keepe at home, or adore abroade: and yet good holy ones, they thinke that Chriſt reſteth daily in their ſoules
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17743:38"/> for their iuſtification; as their filthes lie by their ſides to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their abhominable pleaſures. I meane ſuch, as euer, and at all moments, carrie vpon their backes and about them obligations for the Deuill, adding vanitie vpon vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, iniuſtice vpon iniuſtice; and neuer doe ſo much as once imagine of any recompence, of any ſatisfaction, or reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be made: and yet, as vaine as butter-flies, they will thinke, that at, and in the ſame ſeaſons, and momen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Chriſt doth by iuſtification vouchſafe to adorne, and trimm their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Infinite is the number of ſuch like peruerſe beleeuers, and fooles: of whoſe preſumption, when I ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I cannot but iudge of them, that in their conſciences they are to bee eſteemed the moſt blaſphemous Heretikes, that euer were, in hauing ſuch crooked and doltiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of Chriſt: who as hee is a moſt comfortable and potent Aduocate, for all humble and penitent ſinners, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer refuſing any who with contrite heart ſhall returne to him; ſo likewiſe againſt impenitent ſinners, he hath <hi>in his mouth a double edged ſword,</hi> to chaſtiſe them with eternall malediction; and as it were with the double edge of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble moſt ſharp puniſhment, of loſſe of the glorie of heauen, and of the vndergoing of eternall puniſhment in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe Lake of hell, the damned pit of euerlaſting afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But to Chriſt iuſtifying, to Chriſt ſanctifying, with a moſt humble confidence, and with proſtrate ſoules; let vs all here aſſembled returne, and in a full faith inuocate him, that hee will vouchſafe by the energie of his Almightie bloud, to <hi>cleanſe our conſciences from dead workes, to ſerue him, the liuing God:</hi> that none of vs here preſent, be found of that preſumptuous ranke, to thinke, that although wee liue deliberately and continually in dead workes: yet wee ſhall bee liuing to God through a dead faith, for Chriſts ſake. And here to conclude; Moſt Religious and Chriſtian Auditours (yee, who haue learned, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all reformed Churches, that the bloud of Chriſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17743:39"/> doth ſanctifie and cleanſe from dead workes, all ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences as are iuſtified by faith in the ſame) with what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of ſacred Scripture may I more fitly end, and ſalute you then with that of this our Apoſtle, in his Epiſtle to the Hebrewes; <hi>(Habentes igitur, &amp;c.) Seeing therefore, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. v. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>we may with a firme truſt enter into the holies, in the bloud of Chriſt, by the new way, and a liuing way which hee hath prepared for vs, by the veile of his fleſh: And hauing a high Prieſt ouer Gods houſe; let vs draw neare in a true heart, in the fulneſſe of faith, ſprinkled in our hearts from an euill conſcience, and waſhed in our bodies with pure water: let vs keepe the profeſsion of our faith, without wauering; for hee is faithfull that promiſed: and let vs conſider one another, to prouoke to loue and good workes, not forſaking the fellowſhip or the aſſembly as the cuſtome of ſome is; but let vs exhort, and comfort one another, and that ſo much the more, becauſe yee ſee the day approcheth.</hi> O heauenly perſwaſion! O moſt diuine leſſon! with a firme and an aſſured faith, wee may <hi>walke into the holies in a new and a liuing way,</hi> which Chriſt dying in his bloud, hath dedicated for vs vpon the Croſſe: yet with this condition, moſt dearely beloued, with this prouiſo; that our hearts be <hi>ſincere our conſciences ſprinkled, with this bloud; and our bodies waſhed with this water, and wee bee cleanſed from dead workes, to ſerue the liuing God.</hi> From dead workes, I ſay, wherein we pleaſed Satan, were obſequious to our luſts, and followed our owne concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcences, to liuing workes of pietie, loue, compaſſion, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, feare of God, to ſerue the liuing God: The liuing God, once dying, but now liuing: liuing from aboue, to conſider all our actions; liuing within vs, to giue vs life, mouing, and to ſearch our very reines; liuing in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, ready with reuengefull hand to puniſh the wicked, and with a moſt plentifull arme to reward the vertuous; liuing amongſt vs vpon earth with his grace, to quicken, to ſanctifie vs. What? moſt deuout Chriſtians? ſhall our God be liuing, and we his ſeruants dead? and dead in ſinnefull
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17743:39"/> workes, <hi>Whoſe ſtipend and hire is death and damnation?</hi> What? ſhall the euer-liuing God die an ignominious death? riſe to a moſt glorious life, to quicken vs, to reuiue vs? and will we not bee quickned, be reuiued? The Pellican with bloud ſtroken out of her breaſt, quickneth ſuch of her yong ones, as the Serpent may haue poiſoned or killed: and ſhall not the bloud of our Pellicane Chriſt Ieſus, powred<note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> vpon vs, being ſtroken dead with mortiferous ſinne, quic ken vs, reuiue vs? the Pellicane giueth drops of bloud; Our Pellicane prouideth a bath; the Pellicane ſtriketh her breaſt only; Our Pellicane hath his whole body ſmitten, on euery part, on euery ſide, ſtreaming vpon vs bloud and water: ſhall he not ſanctifie vs? ſhall he not waſh vs, reuiue vs, in iuſtice, pietie, charitie, and other liuing workes of ſanctification? If any here will ſtill take ſinnefull delight in dead workes; it is more then to be doubted, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death and euerlaſting damnation, will more then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon him: But my very ſoule is comforted? for in your very countenances, and aſpects, I ſee your reſolutions, I ſee your Chriſtian determinations, that you will be reuiued; and reuiued in liuing workes of faith, charitie, iuſtice, longanimitie, patience, obedience, pietie, <hi>to ſerue the liuing God, the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt; to whom be all praiſe, honour, and dominion, from hence-forth, for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AMEN.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
